<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Contemplatio mortis, et immortalitatis</title>
            <author>Manchester, Henry Montagu, Earl of, 1563?-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1631</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18023.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112815</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13132</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13132)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1388:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Contemplatio mortis, et immortalitatis</title>
                  <author>Manchester, Henry Montagu, Earl of, 1563?-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 129, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie: and by the assignes of Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1631.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Montagu, Earl of Manchester by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>In English.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary leaf of verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Contemplatio mortis &amp; immortalitatis.</note>
                  <note>Formerly identified as STC 18025.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Immortality --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Eschatology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13132:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13132:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONTEMPLATIO MORTIS, ET IMMORTALI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATIS.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Robert Barker,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent MAIESTIE: and by the Aſſignes of <hi>Iohn Bill. Anno Dom.</hi> 1631.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13132:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13132:2"/>
            <head>CONTEMPLATIO MORTIS ET IM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MORTALITATIS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Hiloſophers, States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; Diuines do all hold, that in this world there are but <hi>tria gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra vitae: Vna eſt actiua: Altera Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiua: Tertia voluptuaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which of theſe is beſt. <hi>Quaeritur:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Actio Contemplationis expers,</hi> is but <hi>vita impolita;</hi> Contemplation, if it take vp all a mans time makes <hi>vitam ſterilem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Voluptuaria vita,</hi> though it bee not <hi>otioſa,</hi> becauſe it is in <hi>actu:</hi> yet is but <hi>deſidioſa occupatio.</hi> Amongſt theſe, who ſo tryes all as I haue done, ſhall finde; that Action pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits moſt, but Contemplation pleaſes beſt: ſpecially that which indebts a man to action. For man
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13132:3"/>was not made for Contemplation onely. It is true, retiredneſſe is is more ſafe then buſineſſe, yet as hee is not happy that is alwayes buſie: ſo a publike man ſhould not alwayes bee ſhut vp in thoughts pleaſing his life in the ſweetneſſe of thinking.</p>
            <p>The ſweetneſſe of thoughts, and vertue of Contemplation, lyes in the right choice of the ſubiect: euery knowing man being ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiue by nature, and of ſo buſie a fancie, as it is happy for him in this way to fall vpon a fit ſubiect.</p>
            <p>Some ancient Fathers, and ſome late Writers haue fixed vpon the loue of God, ſome vpon the Paſſion of Chriſt, ſome vpon the ioyes of Heauen, ſome vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World. So ſeue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall others vpon ſeuerall other ſubiects. All opining, that ſome one is to bee choſen. For who ſo will <hi>viuere ſibi,</hi> muſt <hi>vacare Deo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ego in meo ſolito receſſu in quo à
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13132:3"/>negotijs publicis vacans, mihi ipſi vacaueram</hi> (which was but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) found it fruitfull, vſefull, and delightfull, <hi>cogitare de No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſſimo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quatuor ſunt Nouiſſima,</hi> ſay the Fathers; Death, Iudgement, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and Hell, ſubiects large enough.</p>
            <p>But conſidering I had paſſed ſo much imployment, ſo many of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices in ſeuerall profeſſions, I was ſome while muſing whether any of theſe fitted me to contemplate. In the reuolution of many things, I found, that when Meditation had produced Deuotion, then it applyed it ſelfe to Contemplation. And that true Contemplation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired a ſettlement vpon ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine obiect. Hereupon I made choice of Death and Immortalitie for the ſubiect of my Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation.</p>
            <p>But firſt my thoughts did beate to finde a difference betwixt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and Contemplation.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13132:4"/>
            <p>Meditation or recogitation, I ſaw was but a reiterated thought, proper to production either of good or euill. <hi>Day and night haue I meditated on thy Law,</hi> ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in one Pſalme: in an other, <hi>Why haue they meditated vaine things?</hi> But Diuines doe now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate Contemplation to diuine myſteries. Which affecting our ſoules, and exciting our wils, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth ſome holy reſolution. We meditate, ſaith one, to know God; wee contemplate to loue God. Meditation is the mother, Contemplation the daughter. Yet as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was the crowne of his father, and brought him encreaſe of honour and contentment: the like doth Contemplation to her mother Meditation. When God himſelfe had ſeene the things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſeuerall peeces, hee ſaid, they were <hi>good.</hi> But when hee conſidered the Vniuerſe (as it were in Contemplation) then hee ſaid, Lo, they were <hi>exceeding good.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13132:4"/>
            <p>For Meditation conſiders her obiects peece by peece; but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation ſummes them vp all together, and ſees as in a groſſe, all the ſeuerall beauties of meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons obiects. Meditation is with a man as hee that ſmels the Violet, the Roſe, the Ieſſamy, and the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe flowers, one after the other, diſtinctly. But Contemplation is a ſweet water compounded of them all, wherein you ſhall ſmell all theſe odours together, extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the ſeuerall ſents, which before you ſmelt diuidually. Which extract is farre more fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, then were any of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, though euery one was ſweet alone. This is more elegantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted in the Canticles; where the Spouſe pleates vp her hayre, truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it vp in one knot, to ſhew that wee ſhould not diffuſe our thoughts into varietie of conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, but recollect them by contemplation.</p>
            <p>The end of all is, after many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13132:5"/>changes of meditations and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, to reduce all cogitations to one concluſion. Which is, contemplation of things diuine. Here with a mans ſoule being once affected, hee ſhall hardly obtaine leaue of his thoughts to returne againe to imployment.</p>
            <p>Now to returne <hi>ad meum No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſſimum. What man liueth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) and ſhall not ſee death?</hi> And if after death <hi>Iustus vix ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabitur,</hi> as the Goſpel ſaith; Then wee may well bee fearefull, and had neede be carefull, that wee be not taken vnprepared.</p>
            <p>When I was a young man (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) my care was to liue well. I practiſed <hi>Artem bene viuendi:</hi> when age came vpon me, I ſtudied <hi>Artem bene morien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di,</hi> how to die well.</p>
            <p>It is true, <hi>Iter vitae occupatis non apparet, niſi in fine:</hi> yet when I was <hi>occupatiſſimus, hoc me dulci oblectabam ſolatio, aliquando me victurum mihi.</hi> And this at laſt I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13132:5"/>am come to, <hi>diſponendo, non mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tando me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The couenant of the graue is ſhewed to no man,</hi> ſaith the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: But the watch-word is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to all men: <hi>Sint lumbi prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincti, Lucernae ardentes, ſemper vigilantes.</hi> Lord let me be found in this poſture, when I ſhall bee to dye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nunquam ego fortunae credidi, etiamſi videretur pacem agere.</hi> I haue had my portion as another man, of the worlds fauours: yet did they neuer ſo delight mee, or abuſe mee, as to make mee neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, or to deferre this worke of preparation. I conſidered this, <hi>Guttatim per horas &amp; dies fluit vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi> And although the houre bee not paſt till all the glaſſe be runne, <hi>&amp; nemo multum ex ſtillicidio po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt perdere:</hi> yet the glaſſe then runnes moſt faintly, when it drawes neereſt to effluxion. Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Martha</hi> was full buſie about many things, but was well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13132:6"/>there was onely <hi>vnum neceſſarium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Phyſicians exclaime, <hi>Vita bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, Ars longa eſt.</hi> But Diuines teach, <hi>Ars optima est, vsuendo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere artem bene moriendi.</hi> If this Science bee to learne, when <hi>prae fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Mors eſt;</hi> Thy ſin-ſicke Soule will ſay, <hi>Infelix ego homo, quis me liberabit à corpore mortis huius?</hi> But if thou haſt learnt it betime, then it will reioyce to ſay, <hi>Mihi viuere Chriſtus eſt, &amp; mori, lucrum.</hi> Welcome death, more bleſſed then my birth.</p>
            <p>In the whole courſe of my life I haue alwayes thought the right way to die, was to liue well; and the way to liue well in the world, was to dye betimes to the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mihi Mundus Crucifixus, &amp; ego Mundo:</hi> yet I found it <hi>rem diffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; In mundo viuere, &amp; mundi bona contemnere.</hi> Therfore for aſſiſtants, I tooke three coadiutors; Faith, Hope, Charity. <hi>Charitatemex corde puro, ſpemex conſcientia bona, fidem
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13132:6"/>non fictam.</hi> And for my ſoules health often vſed this preparatiue; <hi>Examen conſcientiae meae. Nam qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cordihabet ſalutem ſuam,</hi> let him euery day, <hi>mane &amp; vespere,</hi> examine his heart. <hi>Quid nocte vel die praecedente,</hi> hath hee thought, hath he ſaid, hath he done? <hi>Et in quo peccati labem inuenerit?</hi> Let him mend it, <hi>cum propoſito efficaci, ſimili non peccare.</hi> This if it be done daily, I dare boldly ſay, <hi>Vix fieri poterit, vt quis moriendo peccet, aut peccando moriatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>Inter</hi> theſe thoughts, I had theſe things in Contemplation.</head>
               <item>1. Firſt, what Death was, and the kinds of death.</item>
               <item>2. Secondly, what feares or ioyes death brought.</item>
               <item>3. Thirdly, when death was to be prepared for, and how.</item>
               <item>4. Fourthly, death approching, what our laſt thoughts ſhould then be.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of theſe I thus reſolued.</head>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13132:7"/>
               <p>THat Death was a fall,
<note place="margin">What death is.</note> which came by a fall. Our firſt fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med father Adam falling, in him wee all fell. <hi>Cecidimus omnes</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Bernard) ſuper acerbum lapidem in luto, vnde inquinati &amp; vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſumus.</hi> Therefore wee needed water in Baptiſme to waſh vs, Blood in the Euchariſt to heale vs.</p>
               <p>This falling ſickneſſe infected not only the perſon, but the nature (ſuch is the infection of euill al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Act) making man that was immortall, ſubiect to Death, as are Birds and Beaſts: whereas before wee were differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from them in this condition, though made of the ſame matter, <hi>Dust.</hi> Yet as wee now ſtand, the fault is ours, if that fall be not our riſe: the aduantage wee haue by Chriſt, being more then the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage wee had by <hi>Adam, ideo qui ſtat, videat ne cadat.</hi> For relapſe may turne vs againe to be as Birds and Beaſts, that haue no ioy, but being; no ſorrow, but dying.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13132:7"/>
               <p>Conſider Death originally or in his owne nature, and it is but a departed breath from dead earth inliuened at firſt by breath caſt vpon it. Take the dimenſion of it, and it is but a point of Time, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriected betweene two extremes. A Parentheſis which interpoſed breakes no ſenſe, when the words meete againe. When <hi>Seneca</hi> was asked, <hi>Quid eſt Mors?</hi> he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Aut finis eſt, aut tranſitus. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus Secundus Philoſophus</hi> ſaid to the Emperour <hi>Adrian, Mors est aeternus ſomnus, Diuitum Pauor, pauperum deſiderium, incerta pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grinatio, ineuitabilis euentus, latro hominis, fuga vitae, reſolutio omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Plato</hi> ſaid it was <hi>Lex Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, Tributum mortalium. Scaliger</hi> defines it to bee, but the ceſſation of the ſoules functions. All men graunt the cauſe of Death was iuſt, yet few can tell, who was the Author, or whats the name or nature of it. <hi>Eſtimemus ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula famâ remotâ quaeramus quid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13132:8"/>ſint, non quid vocentur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Nature it can be nothing for it hath no cauſe efficient,
<note place="margin">The nature of Death</note> but defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. <hi>Poſt mortem nihil eſt, ipſa<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Mors nihil.</hi> It hath no Eſſence, though Exiſtence. It is no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but priuation; no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but <hi>creaturarum ſepultura.</hi> Therefore curiouſly to ſearch the efficient of it, were to labour the eye to ſee darkneſſe. God made it not, ſaith the booke of Wiſedome, nor is it mentioned as any of his workes. God that made all things, ſaw that all things which he had made, were good. <hi>Omne ens bonum, &amp; omne bonum estens.</hi> Therefore good Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid finely, <hi>Lord, thou hast not made Death, wherefore, I beſeech thee, ſuffer not that which thou haſt not made, to reigne ouer that which thou haſt made.</hi> It is no errour to ſay that man made death. For curioſitie (the itch of mans Soule) affecting to know that which God neuer made, which was the euill of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13132:8"/>death, thinking it had been good, to know euill, by deſiring to know it, made it. He that knew all other things, knew not this one thing: that hee knew enough. So diuine a thing is knowledge, that wee ſee, innocencie it ſelfe was ambitious of it. Life did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that was thought but the act of knowledge: knowledge was the life the ſoule looked at. That yet begets a ſtudious ſcrutinie to diſcouer things wee can neuer know. So we ſee, that although Nature be moderate in her deſires, yet conceit is vnſatiable. But ſince God hath reuealed more then we can know, enough to make vs happy; let vs learne ſober knowledge, and contented igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p>Who then was the Author of Death?
<note place="margin">The Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Death.</note> The booke of Wiſedome ſaith, that through enuie of the diuell, death came into the world, and they that hold on his ſide, finde it. But if the Diuell was the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13132:9"/>father, Sinne was the mother. For ſaith Saint <hi>Iames,</hi> ſinne being fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, trauaileth in child-birth like a mother to bring foorth death. <hi>Adam</hi> falling, ſin followed him: Man being tempted, Death at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts him, and by ſinne death entred. Death had no intereſt in man, till ſin had diſpoſſeſſed him of the freehold hee had in God. There was no truſt in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, ſaith <hi>Eliphaz,</hi> but euen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels were charged with folly. And to doe the Diuell right, hee did but perſwade, not compell. It was in mans choice to ſtand or fall. <hi>Adam acceperat poſſe, quod vellet: non velle, quod poſſet: nos accepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; poſſe, quod volumus; &amp; velle, quod poſſumus: ille poſſe non mori, nos non poſſe mori ſic Augustinus.</hi> Power of ſtanding, man had from God, but poſſibilitie of falling from himſelfe. Therefore though wee may thanke our firſt parents for our birth-ſinne; Yet wee may thanke our ſelues for improouing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13132:9"/>of it; wherefore ſaid the old Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie, <hi>Ame, ſalaa me, Domine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All mans natiue vertues were giuen him but in truſt, and vnder a condition. Hee abuſed the truſt, and brake the condition, ſo incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the penaltie. For that is mans nature, euer ſubiect to extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, either dull in want, or wanton in fruition. <hi>Ne moriemini</hi> was a faire warning, but hee cared not for it: when Satan tempted, hee conſented. Had the mind gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the eye, the Apple could not haue beguiled, though it was faire to ſee to. The proud aſpiring thought was hatched in man. The Diuell was but the deuiſer, ſinne was the Author, and wee being partners in the ſinne, ſhared like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the puniſhment. <hi>Facinus quos iniquinat, aequat.</hi> Since then Death ſtole in at the eare, by our hearkening to ill counſell; let vs now caſt it out by the eares, through hearkening to Gods Word: the word of life, the life of Death.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13132:10"/>
               <p>For the name of Death:
<note place="margin">The name of Death.</note> Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> cals it a ſleepe, <hi>Amicus noſter Lazarus dormit.</hi> Of Saint <hi>Steuen</hi> it was ſaid, <hi>and when hee had thus spoken, hee ſlept.</hi> The Patriarkes and Kings of Iudah ſlept with their Fathers. <hi>Tranſitum ad vitam, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui appellant mortem,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard. Sed ideo Scriptura dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes appellat, vt euigilaturos mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè deſperemus. Hee is not dead</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) but ſleepeth, whoſe fleſh doth reſt in hope.</hi> The night ſauours of mortalitie, and ſleepe is but the ſhadow of death, and where the ſhadow is, the body cannot bee farre off. But let it be <hi>Mors à mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu,</hi> which our firſt Parents taſted; or <hi>Mors à mora,</hi> which yet tarries for vs all. Let her bee ſtiled Ladie, miſtreſſe of the world, that will not bee courted, nor yet caſt off. Yet is ſhe but <hi>vox tantum,</hi> a thing next to nothing. <hi>Solo timenda ſono.</hi> Better is it called a transfigurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or tranſmigration from life by death to life againe, <hi>Exitus
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13132:10"/>non tranſitus. Tranſitus quem ire non intelleximus, tranſiſſeſentimus.</hi> The graue is but a withdrawingroome to retyre in for a while, a going to bed to take reſt, ſweeter then ſleepe. And when it is time to riſe, <hi>cum expergiſcar,</hi> then I ſhall bee ſatisfied, ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the meane time it is common to all,
<note place="margin">Death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all.</note> 
                  <hi>Mors etiam ſaxis nomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> venit.</hi> Yet this fauour nature hath done. <hi>Quod grauiſſimum fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, fecit commune, vt crudelitatem fati conſolaretur aqualitas.</hi> Who liues and ſhal not ſee death? <hi>Quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ad vitam naſcitur ad mortem deſtinatur,</hi> it reſpects none. <hi>Equat omnes cinis.</hi> It is as naturall to die as to be borne. <hi>Licet impares naſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, pares morimur.</hi> No ſooner borne, but haſtening to die: <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, morimur.</hi> We come into the world with a ſheete about vs, as no ſonner borne, but going to bee buried. For all this, man is euen with Death. <hi>Nunquam enim mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ingenijs cara in corpore mora est:</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13132:11"/>nay, the good Soule <hi>aegre fert has anguſtias.</hi> Therefore what great thing doth death in haſtening dayes? This ſhewes infirmitie, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then power. Age doth more, <hi>nil enim non longa demolitur vetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas:</hi> Death onely ſhortens time, not life; for lifes time ſhortens by lengthening: <hi>Morimur, quòd mortibus viuimus; morieris, non quia aegrotas, ſed quia viuis.</hi> This all men are to know, that <hi>mortis meritum,</hi> is <hi>peccati debitum.</hi> Both impoſed on man for ſinne.</p>
               <p>Sith then,
<note place="margin">Life but a dying death.</note> it is a Statute made in heauen, <hi>omnibus ſemel mori,</hi> and that life is ſo momentanie, and death ſo certaine; <hi>ſplendemus licèt, Hêu quàm citò frangimur corpora vitrea!</hi> Since life it ſelfe is no true liuing, but a dying being; and ſuch a being, as euery day pants for breath, which nature fawnes vpon it for a while. <hi>Mors &amp; fugacemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequitur virum.</hi> And ſince death is no death, but a going vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and heauens comming vnto
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13132:11"/>vs; How can a man but thinke it a well ſpent life alwayes to be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating vpon death?</p>
               <p>But ſaith <hi>Zenophon, Cur vitam contemnendamputas, &amp; habes?</hi> I will not inquire nor require more of death, but death. <hi>Err as enim, qui in terrogas, Quid ſit mors? Et propter quod mortempetam? Quaeris enim aliquid ſupra ſummum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if a man dye ſhall he liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi> Yes,
<note place="margin">Life after Death.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> we that are in this Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle ſigh, and are burthened, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we would not be vnclothed, but cloathed vpon, that Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie might bee ſwallowed vp of life.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Phoenix ſponte crematur</l>
                  <l>Vt redeat, proprioq ſolet pubeſcere letho:</l>
                  <l>Ste tu corpus coactum</l>
                  <l>Diſcere mutatâ melior procede figurâ.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The bright dayes die into dark nights, but riſe againe a mornings Though the body ſleepe awhile in the duſt, yet ſhal it ariſe after thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13132:12"/>likeneſſe. The Soule which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted for a ſeaſon, ſhall, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> come againe and bee receiued for euer. That bodie which was ſowen a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body, ſhall riſe a ſpirituall bodie: Sow in teares, reape in ioy; who ſo goe forth weeping and carrie precious ſeede, ſhall returne with ioy, and bring their ſheaues with them.</p>
               <p>Yet <hi>caro iſta Pulueries,</hi> this clod of earth muſt lye a while in Duſt. <hi>Sed reſurget tandem</hi> as the Queenes daughter <hi>all glorious within.</hi> For if in this life holineſſe maketh the face of a man to ſhine by an Irradiation from the heart; what ſhall be the beauty of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die glorified? Surely though it be not deifyed: yet ſhall it be purified, perfected, and immortalized. Our vile bodies ſhall be changed, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and faſhioned like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his glorious body. Such glory haue all his Saints.</p>
               <p>If the exchange bee ſuch, who
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13132:12"/>would not be willing, yea, glad to die? <hi>Nilminus eſt hominis occupati, quam viuere. Quos autem felicitas grauat, exclamant illi, Mihi viuere non licet.</hi> It is a good minde to bee content to dye, and willing to liue. But to be willing to dye, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to liue, is the mind of a ſtrong Chriſtian. <hi>Diligimus mortem pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, pariter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> timemus. Ipſe metus te noſter amat.</hi> When the Senator <hi>Cato</hi> was asked a queſtion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Death; <hi>Si Deus (inquit) ille mihi largiatur, vt repueraſcam, valde recuſem. Nec tum me vixiſſe poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, quia bene vixi; nec timeo, mori, quod ex hospitio, non domo, diſcedam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore though death be not to be ſought <hi>in the errour of youth,</hi> as the Preacher ſaith. reſpects it may bee deſired.
<note place="margin">Death de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireable for three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</note> 
                  <hi>Portus eſt aliquando petendus, nunquam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſandus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As firſt, that ſowe may betimes leaue off to ſinne; ſince ſin liues in vs, and leaues vs not till Death. <hi>Dixit Socrates, Appropin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quante
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13132:13"/>morte multò es diuinior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, the Soule that ſoone departs, <hi>facilius ad ſuperos iter fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, quia minùs facis ponderiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> traxit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this paſſage betweene life and death, whats the diſtance? So little, as with the Ancients the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of life was <hi>oculus apertus: Mortis clauſus,</hi> but not <hi>extinctus: nec plus intereſſe putauerunt inter mortem &amp; vitam, quam ictum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi.</hi> Man is onely a winke of life, his life and death ioyned as neere as ioy and griefe; where teares ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe both.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that we might the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner come to liue indeede. <hi>Vita aeterna est illa vita vitalis, iſta eſt tantùm mortalis.</hi> For this cauſe ſaith <hi>Bernard, praecipitat quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ſuam, fuiuri deſiderio laborat, praeſentium taedio.</hi> Men commonly ſay. There is <hi>nullum tempus praeter Nune.</hi> But this preſent is not that which contents the Soule. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis anguſtat gaudia, qui praeſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13132:13"/>acquieſcit.</hi> They are onely creatures of inferiour nature, that are pleaſed with the preſent.</p>
               <p>Man is a future creature, his ſoule lookes at what is beyond this life. <hi>Scrutatur quod vltra mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, futura &amp; praeterita illum delectant; Haec expectatione, illa recordatione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would make a man heauenly proud, but to thinke of how Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine a nature and qualitie his Soule is. The Heathens could ſay it was <hi>Diuinae particula Aurae. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curus</hi> makes it a Spirit mixt of fire and ayre: Others define it to bee a ſelfe-mouing number. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid, <hi>Quid aliud eſt anima, quam Deus in corpore humano hoſpitans?</hi> Neuer could any giue it ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, that either an other, or himſelfe could conceiue it.</p>
               <p>And no wonder that a man cannot conceiue what his Soule is: Becauſe it ſuffered a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure before it ſelfe was. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Admiration</hi> rather then
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13132:14"/>
                  <hi>Search</hi> becomes a man in ſuch a ſecret.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tully</hi> ſaid, <hi>Mihi quidem nunquam perſuaderi potuit, animos dum in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus eſſent mortalibus, viuere; cum exijſſent ex ijs, emori.</hi> Let mee euer worſhip the great God of this little god, my Soule. <hi>Et ne plus vltra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Onely this I know, That to no creature elſe God hath giuen a liuing ſoule, nor is there hope in any creature elſe, but man; and this hope is giuen for ſuſtentation of his ſoule.</p>
               <p>Hee that contemplates theſe things, wil beare himſelfe too lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and thinke himſelfe too good to looke ſo low, as vpon the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunarie things of this life. <hi>Anguſtus, eſt animus quem terrena delectant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How then can this Beautie bee pleaſed to inhabit long <hi>contubernio iſto?</hi> All it needs to care, is but Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulture to that body which once had the Honour to be the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſuch a gheſt: But becauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13132:14"/>many times the houſes of the dead and the vrned bones doe meete with foule hands, for this alſo Nature hath prouided, <hi>vt diſertè ait Maecenas. Nec tumulum quaero, ſepelit Natura relictos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is one of the daily petitions of euery good Soule, <hi>Adueniat Regnum tuum,</hi> Thy Kingdome come, O Lord Yet ſaith <hi>Ambroſe, Hoc nitimur &amp; reluctamur.</hi> For, <hi>Quis ſine querela moritur? Quis non gemens, quis non recuſans exit? Quis cum acceſſerit, non tergiuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, timet, plorat?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all things elſe,
<note place="margin">Mans croſſe Nature.</note> obſerue how contrarily wee carry our ſelues. The labourer from his work haſts to his bed. The Mariner rowes hard to gaine the Port. The Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller is glad when hee is within kenning of his Inne: yet we, when Death comes to put vs into our Port, ſhun it as a rocke. Wee feare what wee ſhould wiſh, and wiſh what we ſhould feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O fortunatiorem Marcellum eo
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13132:15"/>tempore, quo exitum ſuum Bruto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probauit,
<note place="margin">Mans bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter choice.</note> quàm quo populo Romano conſulatum!</hi> Heare, O Chriſtian, what the Pagan ſaith, <hi>Quid ni non timeat, qui mori ſperat?</hi> It is harder to make a true Philoſopher pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of life, then of Death. <hi>Hic ſpe mortis patienter dolet, &amp; taedio doloris libenter moritur. Hunc fert, illam expectat, ſed expectata Mors, tardè venit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am in a ſtraight betwixt two ſaid Saint <hi>Paul, whether to liue in the fleſh were profitable for mee,</hi> and which to chuſe I wote not. Yet at laſt reſolued, liue or die <hi>Chriſt</hi> was to him <hi>aduantage.</hi> Therefore <hi>to bee looſed and to bee with Chriſt</hi> was beſt of all. Till then God grant that I may haue <hi>vitam in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia, mortem verò in deſiderio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So ſhall I fulfill my courſe with ioy, life not deare, nor death grieuous.</p>
               <p>In elder times both wiſe men, great men,
<note place="margin">Life and death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared.</note> and vaine men, had Death in ſuch eſtimation, and ſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13132:15"/>vndervalued life, as they fondly ſaid, Had man beene worthy to know what life was before, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it, hee would haue beene loth to accept it. <hi>Nemo vitam ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciperet, ſi daretur ſcientibus.</hi> Life would haue kept vs in ſlauerie, but that Death freed vs. They counted death but the retreite of life, <hi>&amp; optimum Naturae inuentum:</hi> for by it euery man might make himſelfe happy, no man be longer miſerable then he will. <hi>Placet no vita? viue. Non placet? licet co reuerti, vnde venisti.</hi> They thought no ſtate miſerable, but that which Death could not remedy. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſay they) a wiſe man liues but ſo long as he ſhould, not ſo long as hee can. If Death were not in our power, wee ſhould deſire it more then now wee feare it. <hi>Magiſtra rerum ratio</hi> taught them, that common ſafety lay in Death, <hi>&amp;, inuitum qui ſeruat, idem facit occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denti.</hi> Life was ſubiect to many fortunes, <hi>ſed in eo qui ſcit mori, nil
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13132:16"/>poſſe fortunam.</hi> This made them cheriſh theſe deſperate conceits: <hi>Nil referre; faciatne finem, an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiat.</hi> For though life be not, yet Death is at a mans command. <hi>Mori nihil aliud eſt, quàm velle;</hi> in which reſpect no man could complaine of life. <hi>Quia neminem tenet.</hi> If any man did complaine, this was their wiſh, <hi>Mors vtinam pauidos vitae ſubducere nollet; ſed virtus hanc ſola daret.</hi> In ſcorne ſome ſaid, <hi>Egone expectem vel mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi crudelitatem vel hominis, cum poſſim medio exire tormento, &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſa diſcutere?</hi> But their braueſt conceit was worſt, that it was <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus mortis generoſum,</hi> for a man to be author of his owne death, ſay they, if permitted to deſire death, why ill to giue it to themſelues?</p>
               <q>— Sed furor eſt, ne moriare, mori.</q>
               <p>They ſeemed thus to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their aſſertion, by reaſon as wellas courage. Death is naturall, therefore we come. <hi>Viuere noluit, qui mori non vult,</hi> hee is ſorry that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13132:16"/>he was a man, that is not glad to dye. It is ineuitable, therefore we muſt be reſolute, <hi>feras non culpes, quod vitari non poteſt.</hi> Fooles fly it, old men attend it, wiſe men wiſh it. Nay, ſome ſo prided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in this way, that for Care, Feare or Griefe they would not dye. <hi>Non inferam mihi manus prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dolorem,</hi> nor yet for feare, <hi>ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, timore Mortis mori.</hi> Nor yet the threats of torments. <hi>Sic mori, vincieſt. Sed ſi coeperat ſuspecta eſſe Fortuna, ſi multa occurrebant moleſta tranquillitatem turbantia,</hi> then it was Fortitude to diſpatch themſelues. How, or with what, it mattered not. <hi>Scalpello aperitur ad illam magnam libertatem via, &amp; puncto ſecuritas conſtat,</hi> ſaid <hi>Seneca</hi> when he bled to death. <hi>Cato</hi> will die becauſe the Commonwealth declined; <hi>Nerua,</hi> becauſe the lawes were not kept; <hi>Siluianus,</hi> becauſe he would not liue at the mercy of his enemy; <hi>Lucretia,</hi> to couer a diſhonour.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:13132:17"/>
               <p>But <hi>Plato</hi> and his <hi>Socrates</hi> were of another minde: Death was to be expected till Nature called for it, or Iuſtice tooke it. For Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſake men may <hi>ponere animas,</hi> but <hi>ſuas,</hi> not for oſtentation, nor in diſcontent. <hi>Inde facult as fuit non ponendi animam, ſed pendendi. Bona res eſt mori ſuâ morte.</hi> Life was giuen to manage to the vtmoſt, and to make the beſt of it. Euery one was heere ſet ſentinell, not to depart the place till his Captaine calls him off. <hi>Non eſt optima, quae placet, ſed quaedecet:</hi> That Death was beſt which was well recollec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, quietly ſuffering what it could not poſſibly preuent. <hi>Fortiter ille facit, qui miſer eſſe poteſt.</hi> It is not enough to die with a Romane courage, nor that the cauſe of Death be iuſt; but it muſt bee alſo neceſſarie, vnſought, ineuitable.</p>
               <q>But let goe this diſcourſe, my Contemplation lyes another way.</q>
               <p>The kindes of Death as of life,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13132:17"/>are two: The one bodily,
<note place="margin">The kinde of death.</note> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall. As bodily life is the coniunction of body and ſoule: So bodily Death is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of ſoule and body. And as a godly man hath three degrees of life:</p>
               <p>The firſt in this life, when Chriſt liues in him; for the ſoule of a good mans ſoule is the Spirit of God within.</p>
               <p>The ſecond when his body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes to the earth, and his ſoule to God that gaue it.</p>
               <p>The third at the end of the world, when body and ſoule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnited ſhal enioy heauen: So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a wicked man hath three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct deaths. Dead in ſinne while he liues, dead in ſoule when hee dyes, dead in body and ſoule when both are adiudged to eternall condemnation. <hi>Malis fit mors ſine morte, fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fine fine, defectus ſine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu. Quia mors viuit, fints ſemper incipit, &amp; deſicere defectus neſcit.</hi> To labour not to lye is labour
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13132:18"/>in vaine, it is to deferre, not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid. To forget to dye, and hope to liue is dangerous ſecuritie. This let a wiſe man doe, <hi>quod ne ceſſe eſt, ne timeat; quod incertum eſt, ſemper expectet.</hi> Seeke not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation againſt death, but let Death bee thy conſolation; for there is no comfort againſt death, but in death. <hi>Supremum necoptes, nec metuas diem. Mortem optare, malum, timere, peius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to make Death eaſie: Thinke of the glory that followes it. Who will not endure a few pangs for infinite pleaſures? The bitter pill promiſing health is ſwallowed willingly. <hi>Mors non anfert vitam, ſed in melius transfert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the aſpect of Death may not trouble thee, looke not vpon Death in death, but looke beyond it. Thinke not ſo much of it, as of the happineſſe that comes by it. <hi>Erit ſomnus dilectis, initium refri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerij, ſcala montis, haereditas ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, Ianua vitae, ingreſſus in taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum.</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:13132:18"/>Therefore ſaith <hi>Iob, From ſixe troubles it deliuereth thee, &amp; in ſeptima,</hi> that is, at point of death, <hi>non tanget te malum.</hi> Fit your ſelfe for it, and you will neuer feare it, doe by it as you doe in other things, when you would goe ſleepe, you put off your cloathes, you draw the curtaines, and goe to bed. Thus as it were acting ſleepe, before you goe to ſleepe. So addreſſe your ſelfe to death before hand. Bring your ſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it, that when it comes you may entertaine it, <hi>non vt hoſtis, ſed vt hoſpes,</hi> not as a foe, but as a friend: not as a ſtranger, but as a gueſt that you had long looked for; and bid welcome Death, more bleſſed then thy Birth. What a griefe is it to ſee ſome great men build ſtately hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as if they ſhould alwayes liue, and yet they to liue as if they had but mortall ſoules!</p>
               <p>It is good counſell; <hi>Effice mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tibi familiarem, vt poſſis, cum
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13132:19"/>ſors tulerit, illi laetus &amp; alacriter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiam exire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe Philoſophers were more mortified, who had their graues alwayes open before their gates, that going out or comming in, they might alwayes thinke of Death. Good <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of Arimathea built his Sepulchre in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of his garden. So doe thou, amid all thy pleaſures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, thinke of death, and that wil coole and temper all thy vaine deſires. It will ſo qualifie thee to the world, and the world to thee, as thou wilt not much care for it.</p>
               <p>In this world wee are all <hi>Beno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> the ſonnes of Sorrow. The way to Heauen is by weeping croſſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hi motus animorum atq haec certamina tanta</l>
                  <l>Pulueris exigut tactu co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>preſſa quieſcunt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>It is obſerued, that moſt of other creatures liue long, but dying, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh all to nothing. Man that is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13132:19"/>ſhort-liu'd, he dying, liues eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. Thinke but of this, and you will thinke as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> did, that life was little better then hell, were it not for the hope of Heauen.</p>
               <p>Surely Chriſt would not haue dyed, but that wee might die with ſafety. Hee by death in death, did deliuer vs from death. And did Chriſt dye for mee, that I might liue with him? I will not therefore deſire to liue long from him. It is a token of little loue to God, to be loth to goe to God. All men goe willingly to ſee him whom they loue. <hi>Our brother</hi> Ioſeph <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,</hi> therefore though with <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> I cannot ſay, <hi>I will goe ſee him before I dye.</hi> Yet Lord let mee dye that I may ſee <hi>him whom my ſoule loueth.</hi> Liuing I cannot, but dying I ſhall.</p>
               <p>Let no difficulties hinder, for ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fall none paſſeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Paradiſe, but by burning Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims. The way to Canaan is cumberſome, but knowing that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13132:20"/>our iourney leades to the land of promiſe, wee paſſe it pleaſantly. Yet before wee come at Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, we take in our way the valley of teares. The ſwift Riuer of Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan muſt be croſſed, before wee come to the ſweet Waters of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loam.</p>
               <p>Let no delights tempt you; proſperous fortunes may hinder a cheerefull dying: but if pleaſures of life allure not, feares of death will neuer trouble. <hi>Neminem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſa conuincunt, niſi quem ſecunda decipiunt. Adam</hi> was ſet vpon in Paradiſe, <hi>Iob</hi> on the dunghill: yet Iob <hi>fortior in ſtercore, quam</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>in Paradiſo.</hi> The very place of pleaſure is dangerous. In Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe <hi>Adam</hi> could not be innocent, but out of Paradiſe he was a good man. For any thing in life, loſe not the cauſe of life, nor iudge not of things by the face of things. For life and death haue deceiueable vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards: vnder the faire face of life lurkes griefe: vnder the foule fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13132:20"/>of death (which is but fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) lies felicity. Take off the mask and you ſhall change your minde; loath that you loued, and loue that you loathed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ita habitu caſto, cum non ſit caſta, videtur,</l>
                  <l>Mors, praeter cultum, nil meretricis habet.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Now for the freedomes that come by Death.
<note place="margin">Freedo by deat</note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt it frees from all worldly iniuries:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <hi>Mors multorum malorum finis, nullius boni.</hi> Heere good men doe but liue, and ſuffer <hi>benè agere, &amp; male pati.</hi> It is their portion and <hi>it is good for mee</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>that I haue beene afflicted. Non ſentire mala, non eſt hominis; ſed non ferre, non eſſet viri.</hi> Sufferings are grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter trials then actions.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it ends all miſeries.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <hi>Man in miſery</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>longs for death, and digs for it more then trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Mors finis eſt, non poena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay ſaith one, <hi>Nec finis, nec paena
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13132:21"/>bonis lex eſt, non paena, perire.</hi> Death ends ſinnes, not life: it reformes, but doth not deſtroy Nature. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum eſt Sepultura, virtutum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> it frees vs from all corporall infirmities. <hi>Mors omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um dolorum ſolutio.</hi> Life it ſelfe is a diſeaſe, and we dye by corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of humours, whether they be of body or manners: who thinke to heale all infirmities with an eaſier plaiſter then Death, <hi>Delineamenta potius quam remedia podagraeſuae ponunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> it frees vs from all bodily labours. So ſaith the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Bleſſed are they that die in the Lord, they rest from their labours. Adeo iuuat occupatum mori.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> it eaſes vs of all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles. <hi>Refrigeries eſt animae.</hi> Refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Soule. Were wee but in a throng, wee thinke that man at eaſe who gets out firſt. <hi>Noah,</hi> when hee had beene toſſed but a yeere vpon the waters, Mount
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13132:21"/>Ararat was to him a gladſome place; for there the Arke reſted. So likewiſe miſcrable man after many weariſome yeeres, toſſed vp and downe the world as in a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſea, will bee glad of Death as of Mount Ararat, a reſting place for his tyred Soule. As an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſe patiently vndergoeth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeeres labour to bee made a Freeman, or as a bondman waites for the yeere of Iubile: So doth the Soule for her deliuerance.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> death doth vs not the leaſt pleaſure, in freeing vs from phantaſmes and vaine pleaſures. Pleaſure may ſtand with inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, for God loues to ſee his creatures happy: But common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the pleaſure of the body, is the poyſon of the ſoule. A man ſmothered in Roſes meetes with Death, though in ſweetneſſe. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licatas enim mentes eneruat feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas.</hi> In vaine mirth, there is no true ioy, nor gladneſſe in laughter. <hi>Nam res eſt ſeuera verum
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13132:22"/>gaudium.</hi> Delight in pleaſures, and you ſhall finde your greateſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures become your bittereſt paines in their loſſe. A man whoſe ſoule is conuerſant with God, finds more pleaſure in the deſart, and in death, then in the Palace of a Prince.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The benefits that come by death.</head>
               <p>FVlneſſe of grace,
<note place="margin">The benefits by death.</note> which heere we haue but in part. <hi>Viuere ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linthomines,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> vt perfectiſint: Mori volunt, &amp; perfecti ſunt.</hi> Heere wee haue but <hi>arrham Spiritus,</hi> there we ſhall haue <hi>pretium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> perfection of glory; <hi>Erimus participes, non spectatores gloriae.</hi> Enioy with theſe eyes, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem illam beatificam,</hi> ioy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable. <hi>And</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>your ioy ſhall no man take from you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> inſeparable fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Chriſt. <hi>They follow the Lambe whitherſoeuer hee goeth.</hi> There wee ſhall bee married to him, heere we are but contracted.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13132:22"/>
                  <hi>Deſponſabo te mihi,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Thoſe fauours and loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokens I haue heere receiued, doe but inflame, not ſatisfie deſires, and I am willing to part with them, leſt they ſhould make mee loth to depart to him that gaue them: <hi>Meretricius eſt amor plus amicum, quàm ſponſum diligere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> it brings mee where I would be, into my owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, into Paradiſe, where I ſhall meete, not as in the <hi>Elyſium</hi> of the Poets, <hi>Catones, Scipiones, &amp; Scaeuolas,</hi> but <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iaeob:</hi> The Patriarks my Fathers, the Saints my Brothers, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels my Friends, my wife, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, kindred and ſeruants that are gone before me, and doe there attend mee, looking and longing for my ariuing there. Therefore with <hi>Dauid</hi> I will ſay, <hi>Lord, when ſhall I come and appeare before thee? Like as the Hart panteth for the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brookes, ſo panteth my ſoule for thee, O God. I had rather be a doore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13132:23"/>keeper in thy houſe, then dwell heere though in chambers of pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="division">
               <head>Touching the ſecond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Diuiſion. II.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The feares or ioyes that death brings.</head>
                  <p>NAturally men feare Death,
<note place="margin">The feares of death.</note> becauſe it ends being, which Nature would preſerue: Rachel <hi>mourned for her children and would not be comforted, becauſe they were not.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a Serpent, it was feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. But when God bids, Feare not to take it vp, it may well be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. <hi>Timeat mortem qui Deum non timet, ſed ſi ſperare deſideras, deſine timere.</hi> It is well ſaid, <hi>Pompa Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis magis terret quam mors ipſa.</hi> Groanes, convulſions, and a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couloured face ſhew death terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But that Philoſopher is not to bee followed, who to prepare himſelfe the better for death, ſet forth death moſt fearefully: nor
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13132:23"/>yet that Emperour to be praiſed, who ſo little eſteemed of death, that hee dyed in a complement.</p>
                  <p>Feare of death kills vs often, where death it ſelfe can doe it but once. The Philoſophers thought, that if death (as bad as men count it) were not mingled with bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, men would runne to it with deſire and indiſcretion. <hi>Ergo mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem concupiſcentes, &amp; timentes, aeque obiurgat Epicurus.</hi> It is true, life would not willingly be troubled with too much care, nor death with too much feare. Feares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray, cares trouble thoſe ſuccours that reaſon would yeeld to both. <hi>Multi ad fatum venêre ſuum, dum fata timent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Feares multiply euils, Faith diminiſhes them: yet moſt men wiſh, <hi>vt mors potius ſemel incidat, quam ſemper impendeat,</hi> becauſe nothing is ſo painefull as to dwell long vnder the expectation of ſome great euill.</p>
                  <p>Conſcience of dying, giues
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13132:24"/>the right ſence of death, and the true ſcience of liuing. For by death <hi>abſoluitur anima, reſoluitur corpus, gaudet quòd abſoluitur, quòd reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitur, non ſentit.</hi> Therefore ſaid the Heathen man, <hi>Non nego poenas eſſe quibuſdam poſt mortem, ſed quid ad mortem, quod poſt mortem eſt?</hi> If there be any feares in death, ſaith a wiſe man; <hi>Quare iuuenes non timent fieri ſenes?</hi> But it is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of feare to make dangers greater, helpes, leſſe then they are.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> had word brought him that his deare and onely ſonne was dead: <hi>Scio,</hi> ſaid hee, <hi>me genuiſſe mortalem.</hi> The ſonnes condition, ſatisfied the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers paſſion without more words. Hee can neuer be at eaſe, nor liue contentedly, that liues continually in feare of death. <hi>Nil in morte metuamus, ſi nihil timendum vita noſtra commiſit.</hi> There is no ſuch gentle remoouall of all life's diſcontents, as a quiet death.</p>
                  <p>Hee that knowes not how to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13132:24"/>end his time, hath loſt all his time. <hi>Neſcire mori miſerrimum.</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates <hi>de morte diſputabat vſque ad ipſam.</hi> When <hi>Otho</hi> and <hi>Cato</hi> had prepared all things for their death they ſetled themſelues to ſleepe: when they awaked, and found themſelues vpon the ſtroke of execution, all they ſaid, was, <hi>Vita ſupplicio data eſt, mors remedio.</hi> Cruell tyrants haue beene told to their faces, that their threates of death, were promiſes of life. Their ſwords were fauours to the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. Mortall wounds made them immortall. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuere non poteſt, qui mori non audet.</hi> Though it be true, that it is in vaine to feare what wee cannot ſhunne, and feare of death, as a tribute due to Nature, is a weakeneſſe: yet feares be not alwayes ill ſymptomes before death, nor in death: at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant nature will reluct for loue ſake to keepe ſtill her being. But grace thus diſtinguiſhes of being. To the wicked the beſt thing of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13132:25"/>all were not to haue beene. <hi>Non naſci optimum.</hi> His next beſt were to liue long. It was ill with him that he was borne, worſe, that he muſt dye: for hee not being ſure of a better, would faine be ſure of this. Conſcious to himſelfe that this dying life, will bring him to a liuing death. His hope is no longer then his breath. His word is <hi>Dum spiro, ſpero;</hi> he flutters <hi>inter mortis metum, &amp; vitae tormentum: viuere nolit, &amp; merineſcit.</hi> With good men it is otherwiſe, to them the beſt thing of this life is to haue been, for this leades the way <hi>ad beatitudinem patriae,</hi> to the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their faith. <hi>Quid huius vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere eſt,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>ſed dijs mori.</hi> His word is <hi>Cum expiro, ſpero:</hi> his hopes faint not, when his breath failes him. <hi>Patienter viuit &amp; delectabiliter moritur.</hi> To this man, <hi>mori qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>primum</hi> is his rather: for that ends miſery, and begins felicitie. There is no man ſo vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant as the beleeuer. Therefore he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13132:25"/>ſaith vnto his ſoule, <hi>Why art thou caſt downe, O my ſoule? Why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? Waite on God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Soule and Soule are differenced in dying, as well as liuing.
<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of ſoules as well in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</note> The Atheiſt dares not die for feare of <hi>non eſſe.</hi> The ill liuer dares not die, for feare of <hi>male eſſe.</hi> The doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſcience dares not die, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciendo;</hi> whether hee ſhall be, not be, or be damned.</p>
                  <p>Onely the good man dares and deſires to die, hee is aſſured of his hope, his hope is full of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. <hi>I am thy ſaluation,</hi> ſaith his Sauiour: to the other theend of theſe preſent miſerable miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, is the beginning of worſe, and ſuch as death it ſelfe cannot terminate: for that would be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe enough; if they had but hope, there would bee an end at laſt: the greateſt pleaſure they would deſire, is, the act of death, ſo that might end their ſorrowes: but their conſcience will not let
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13132:26"/>them lye, or flatteringly perſwade them: <hi>Adueniet tandem quae non ſperabitur hora.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This they know, and grieue to thinke, that Tophet is prepared for the bad, and Paradiſe for the good. As the tree falleth, ſo it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: and as death leaueth thee, ſo iudgement ſhall finde thee: hee that liues ill, ſeldome dyes well. Liue well, and you cannot but die well: practiſe well doing, and you ſhall haue the comfort of well dying.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sed quàm amarum erit hoc tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore corporis &amp; animae ſeparatio?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Body and ſoule par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> We ſee old acquaintance cannot part without teares. <hi>Quid facient inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè familiares, quales ſunt corpus &amp; anima, quae ab ipſo vtere ita iucun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimè vixerint?</hi> If the Oxe loweth when his fellow is taken from him that drew the plough with him, <hi>qualem mugitum</hi> ſhall wee giue when ſoule and body part? <hi>Siccinè ſeparas amara Mors: Sic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinè ſeparas,</hi> ſaith the Booke of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13132:26"/>Kings? The Spirit at this time may be willing, but the fleſh will be loth. <hi>Egrè amittitur, quod val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè amatur.</hi> Faith will aſſure, God is thy father; but nature will tell thee, She is thy mother, and thou mayeſt not yet leaue her. In this conflict take heede the mothers ſide preuaile not. Shee will play <hi>Naomi's</hi> part, perſwade thee ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to ſtay and enioy the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of Moab yet a while lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But reſolue thou with <hi>Ruth,</hi> to ſee what entertainment is for thee in Bethleem, for there thou ſhalt finde a <hi>Boaz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In iſta hora,</hi> euery man will make <hi>Balaams</hi> ſuite, (for no man would be miſerable, if it were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to deſire to be happy) but ſuch a wiſh onely will not ſerue. He muſt <hi>piè viuere,</hi> that will <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curè mori.</hi> We all deſire to ſhut vp our laſt Scene of life, with <hi>In ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus tuas, Domine, commendo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum meum.</hi> But it is not the laſt words a man vtters that doe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13132:27"/>his Soule. Remember how in thy life thou haſt entertained Gods Spirit: for as wee vſed his in this life, ſo hee will vſe ours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death. <hi>Qualem quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſe fecerit in hac vita, talem ſe inueniet exiens ab hac vita.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At this houre what would a man giue for the redemption of his ſoule? but poore indigent man, neuer was any ſo rich that could pay the ranſome of his own ſoule. A diſpleaſed mercy, askes greater ſatisfaction then thou canſt giue. <hi>Laeſa patientia fit furor.</hi> Now thou goeſt to giue account of thy Stewardſhip: that is, <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris amiſſi, mali commiſſi, boni o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsi.</hi> And thy Soule already knowes, <hi>in conſcientia tua,</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it goes, <hi>quando egreditur è cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore tuo.</hi> And although thou canſt carry nothing elſe with thee, yet this thou canſt not leaue behinde thee; Which is <hi>liber conſcientiae tuae,</hi> that will tell thee whither thou goeſt, and what thou ſhalt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13132:27"/>looke for. <hi>Tunc quaſi loquentia tua opera dicent; Tu nos egiſti. Tua opera ſumus, non te deſeramus: ſed tecum ſemper erimus, tecum pergemus ad Iudicium.</hi> Man is a great flatterer of himſelfe, but conſcience is alwayes iuſt, and will neuer chide thee wrongfully. It alwayes takes part with God, againſt a mans ſelfe. It is <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus domeſticus,</hi> that will tell what you doe at home, and, ſaith the booke of Wiſedome, <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe condemned of her owne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is euer timerous, and being preſſed with conſcience, forecaſteth grieuous things. Nemo ſeueriorem ſeipſo habet iudicem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a man will take his ayme by the beſt men that euer dyed. That of <hi>Dauid, Ezechias,</hi> yea and of Chriſt himſelfe (as a man) is able to amaze any man. When as our Sauiour Chriſt at the point of death, ſaid, <hi>Father, if it be thy will, let this Cup paſſe from me.</hi> When <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, <hi>Saue Lord, for thy
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13132:28"/>mercy ſake; for in death there is no remembrance of thee.</hi> And <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias</hi> wept ſore, when hee was bid, <hi>Put thy houſe in order, for thou muſt die. Si Prophetae, ſi Apoſtoli, ſi Martyres, ſi Chriſtus ipſe,</hi> was thus troubled at the houre of death: wretched man that I am, what ſhall I doe? Euen as Chriſt bids me. <hi>Bee of good cheere, for I haue ouercome death. Mors morte redempta eſt.</hi> Now there is aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in death: that death which was the wages of ſinne, is made the reward of righteouſneſſe: and in theſe forenamed perſons it was not death, but the curſe of the Law that went with death, which Chriſt in our perſons, and theſe other perſons in themſelues, feared.</p>
                  <p>When Chriſt was to leaue the world, and his Diſciples to the world, he left them this word for their learning and their comfort: <hi>If you loued mee you would reioyce, becauſe I ſaid, I goe to the Father. In
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13132:28"/>my Fathers houſe are many dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. I goe to prepare a place for you, that where I am you may be alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now that death hath ouercome death, and Faith hath ſecured feare: <hi>nec me taedeat viuere, nec ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meo mori.</hi> What can hee feare in Death, whoſe death is his hope? <hi>Right precious in the ſight of God, is the death of his Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>See then what makes men wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or loth to die.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſecro te Lucili,</hi> ſaid <hi>Seneca, cur timeat laborem vir, mortem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo?</hi> It is the preſent condition of men in this world, that makes them willing, or loth to die. Nor life, nor death, are alike to all men: ſome can as willingly leaue the world, nay dye, as others can forbeare the Court. And as men differ in their condition, ſo doe they in their acceptation of Death: ſome pleaſant their liues, as if the world ſhould alwayes laugh vpon them. <hi>Et poſt mortem nulla voluptas.</hi> Theſe would doe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13132:29"/>any thing rather then die. Others liue as if they came into the world but to act a ſad mans part and dye, theſe wiſh a change, hoping it will bee a benefit. Therefore well ſaid the ſonne of <hi>Syrach, O death, how acceptable is thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance vnto him whoſe ſtrength fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, that is now in his laſt age, and vexed with all things: and to him that despaireth and hath loſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience!</hi> But contrariwiſe, <hi>O death, how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that lyeth at reſt in his poſſeſsions! vnto the man that hath nothing to vexe him, and that proſpereth in all things: yea, to him that is yet able to receiue meate!</hi> Certainly to this man that thus liues at eaſe in delicacie with affluence of all things; (for euen to vſe happineſſe is as difficult as to forbeare it) to him it is a ſad and bitter meditation, to thinke that death muſt take him from all theſe ioyes, wherein his heart tooke pleaſure.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:13132:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O quam amara mors mundum amantibus!</hi> Euery poore content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment glues his affections to that he likes. When as the beſt of this worlds contentments are but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible. If thy heart bee ſet on Heauen, thy ſoule will haue no pleaſure in theſe low things, looke vpward. <hi>Os homini ſublime dedit, coelum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tueri.</hi> The minde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templating Heauen, walkes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond eye ſight, and at ſo farre a diſtance diſcernes God, as if hee were at hand, there is his true ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, to conuerſe with God. Who euer they bee that dwell in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of heauenly things, goe off rich in thoughts, ſatisfied in their expectation.</p>
                  <p>For an antidote againſt Death, hate ſinne, and the pleaſures thereof, then will death bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, nor life dolefull: nay, death it ſelfe looking thee in the face, knowing thy heart, will change countenance, looke vpon thee <hi>facie non horrendâ, ſed blandâ,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13132:30"/>non terribili, ſed amabili.</hi> This very day of death. <hi>Dies iſte, quem tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam extremum aliqui reformidant, tibi aterni natalis erit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The good mans hope is euen in death: the world-louer ends both hope and happineſſe when he dyes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plato</hi> diſcourſing vnto one, <hi>de contemptu mortis,</hi> and ſpeaking ſtrangely vpon it, was anſwered, <hi>Fortiùs loqueris, quàm viuis. At ille dicebat non quemadmodum viueret, ſed quemadmodum viuendum eſſet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How euer the Contemplation of death pleaſes, yet the ſufferance of death pinches. A man ſatisfied that death is nothing but a bridge, to paſſe him ouer to an other ſhore where life ſtands, and lookes for his landing: yet while hee is vpon the Bridge, (which is but a ſhort ſtep betwixt two liues) his vertiginous braine wil grow gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and hee will before troubled in the paſſage.</p>
                  <p>Did not the word <hi>Ibis ad Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres,</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:13132:30"/>ſweeten the contemplation, as did that wood caſt by <hi>Moſes</hi> into the the waters of Marah, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning bitterneſſe into ſweetneſſe: the thought of death (though it be but a gathering to our Fathers) would be an vnpleaſing contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation.</p>
                  <q>But feares being paſt, which are but ſhadowes, ſet off ioyes the better. Therefore now to ſee</q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What ioyes death brings.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OVt of the bitter came ſweet,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ioyes brought by death.</note> ſaid <hi>Sampſon.</hi> When wee thinke vpon the ſeparation of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule, then it is a ſweet contemplation, to conſider the coniunction of our bodies and ſoules with Chriſt: which being once made by the bond of the Spirit in this life, ſhall neuer after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards be cancelled. For let death, wilde beaſts, or birds, deuoure and teare the body from the ſoule, yet neither body nor ſoule are thereby ſeuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt. <hi>Non curo</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13132:31"/>
                     <hi>Ignatius) ſi ferarum dentes me mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luerint modo pura fiam farina Christo.</hi> And yet the body thus conſumed, liues not in the graue or belly of the beaſt, nor yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues life or ſenſe from the ſoule while it is in this ſeate, vntill the great Aſſizes, that generall <hi>Venite</hi> comes. But then, looke what the condition of Chriſt was in his death, the like ſhal be of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. The body &amp; ſoule of Chriſt were ſeuered, as farre as Heauen and the Graue were diſtant: and yet neither of them were ſeuered from the godhead, but both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſted in his perſon: ſo likewiſe our bodies and ſoules, though rent and pulled in ſunder milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of miles diſtant, yet neither of them is ſeuered or diſioyned from Chriſt our head. <hi>Qui prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dixit, reuixit,</hi> this ſerues to work it.</p>
                  <p>Humane wiſedome cannot comprehend this. Weake faith lookes for meanes, and is put to ſhifts when ſhee ſees meanes faile.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:13132:31"/>But omnipotency workes by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probabilities and tels vs. There is no faith, where there is either meanes or hopes. Difficulties and improbabilities are the obiects of Faith. <hi>Through the Spirit</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) wee waite for the hope of righteouſneſſe in faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet in nature we ſee that in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeaſon, trees which ſeeme as dead, reuiue againe in the Spring, becauſe the body, graines &amp; armes of the trees, are ioined to the root, where the ſap lyes all the Winter, and by meanes of coniunction, it conueyes vegitation to all parts of the tree; euen ſo mens bodies haue their winter, when they are turned into duſt. <hi>Homo arbor inuerſa, cuius Radix in caelis, rami in terra.</hi> Their life is hid in Chriſt with God. Yet in the day of reſurrection, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this myſticall coniunction, diuine and quickening vertue ſhall ſtreame from Chriſt to his Elect, and cauſe them to reſurge from the graue, to life eternall. For the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13132:32"/>head wil not be without the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: where he is, there they ſhall be alſo.</p>
                  <p>It is noted how in that tranſfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the body of <hi>Moſes</hi> which was hid in the valley of Moab, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the hill of Tabor, which aſſures that this body of ours, lodge it where you will, is not loſt, but layed vp to bee raiſed in glory, as it was laid downe in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. The incineration and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipation of this duſt, ſhall haue a recollection in that day of reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
                  <p>In the valley of dead bones, did not the Spirit ſay to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Propheſie vpon theſe bones, and ſay, <hi>O ye dry bones, I will cauſe breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to enter into you; I will lay ſinewes vpon you, and will bring vp fleſh, and you ſhall liue?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If any thinke,
<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the reſurrection of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and the iuſt</note> this <hi>Reſurge</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, which is ſo wonderfull, is not peculiar, but common vnto all, both good and bad, (as good men loue not to bee happy alone)
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13132:32"/>its truth, yet, it is not by the ſame cauſe, nor to the ſame end. For the wicked riſe by the power of Chriſt, to be iudged and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But the godly riſe by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Chriſts reſurrection, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue eternall life. <hi>Vita mortem aſſumpſit, vt mors vitam aſſumeret.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore they collect truely, who ſay, that the rotting of our bones is no death, but a being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe; and that ſleepe muſt needs be ſweet, which hath peace with reſt, and reſts in ſafety.</p>
                  <p>Awake then thou that ſleepeſt, ariſe, come and liue: hee whom thou loueſt, ſleepeth, but thou wilt come to awake him: till when his couch of eaſe, is his coffin, the graue his bed, wherein he lyes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer troubled with dreames or fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, what ſhall become of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, till it riſe againe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am the reſurrection and the life;</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>He that beleeueth, though hee were dead, yet ſhall hee liue:</hi> the arreſt of Death ſhall not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13132:33"/>alwayes keepe him. Well ſaid S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> The bodies of Saints ſhall bee raiſed, <hi>tanta falicitate, quanta felicitate,</hi> with as much eaſe as happineſſe. <hi>Nam mors tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum intermittit vitam, non eripit;</hi> death doth not diſanul, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continue life. By our riſing, wee are remitted to our better right, a life which neuer dyes, a morning which hath no Eue nor ending. Me thinkes I heare death ſay of life, as <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> ſaid of Chriſt: <hi>He that commeth after mee, is before me.</hi> Which is life.</p>
                  <p>O ſweet word Life. The beſt Monaſyllable in the world. Gods owne Attribute. <hi>Deus viuit.</hi> And <hi>my ſoule</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>ſhall liue, for my Redeemer liueth.</hi> And is this life, but the child of this word Death? then bleſſed alſo bee the word Death, the mother of life. I will no more call thee <hi>Marah,</hi> but <hi>Naomi;</hi> for thou art not bitter, but ſweet; more pleaſant, though ſwifter in thy gate then the Row
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13132:33"/>or Hinde. The Stoike could ſay, <hi>Mors eſt quae efficit, vt naſci non ſit ſupplicium.</hi> But what ſaith <hi>S. Iohn? I heard a voice from heauen, ſaying, Write, Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, whoſe workes follow them, they die no more, death hath no more power ouer them, all teares are wiped from their eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Compare together the benefits of life and death, and you ſhall clearely ſee, how that death which ſeemes to diſpoſſeſſe vs of all, puts vs in poſſeſſion of more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that al.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Per varios caſus, per tot diſcrimina reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tendimus in Latium, ſedes vbi fata quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</l>
                     <l>Oſtendunt.—</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>It is but being which wee haue by Nature, or by Birth; our bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being is by Grace; but our beſt being is in glory: there wee cannot bee, till death haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed vs thither. <hi>Eſſe naturae eſt, benè eſſe gratiae, optimum eſſe gloriae.</hi> Better therefore is our laſt being by death, then was our firſt being by birth. <hi>Dici<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> beatus ante obitum
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:13132:34"/>nemo.</hi> Birth brought mee into the world, but that was miſery, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no vacation to ſorrowes. <hi>Ne natalem quidem excipit.</hi> For crying was the firſt note of my being. <hi>Calamitatis futurae propheta.</hi> Death carries me from a world of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to a world of felicities. <hi>Dies mortalis eſt fatalis Natiuitas.</hi> Heere I dwell in a houſe of clay, whoſe foundation is duſt: Death brings to an habitation made without hands, euerlaſting in the heauens. <hi>Ad excelſa ſublatus, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter felices currit animus, excipit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> illum coetus ſacer.</hi> Birth brought mee to conuerſe, and haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with men, death brings mee to haue communion with Saints, and fellowſhip with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels; yea, to enioy <hi>viſionem illam beatificam.</hi> The immediate fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God and Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Old father <hi>Iacob,</hi> when he was told of his ſonne <hi>Ioſephs</hi> power in Egypt, was not ſatisfied to heare of his honours, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13132:34"/>of his life: intimating that life to come, is better then all the honours that are in Egypt, or fortunes that are on earth: nor yet did <hi>Ioſephs</hi> life content him, without being preſent with him, and therefore ſaid, <hi>I will goe downe and ſee him:</hi> counting it better to behold with the eye (and yetmoſt ſinnes begin and creepe in at the eyes) then to walke in deſires. Implying, that the beſt things that are, pleaſure vs not in their being, but in our enioying them.</p>
                  <p>What then ſhall bee the ioy,
<note place="margin">The ioy ſoule &amp; dy at the meeting.</note> when ſoule and body ſeparated for a ſeaſon, ſhall meete againe in ioy, and mutually enioy one the other? The ſenſe of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and contentment did well appeare in that meeting betwixt <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whom mutuall loſſe and ſeparation for a while, did more endeare each to other.</p>
                  <p>Intermiſſion of comfort hath this aduantage, that it ſweetens our delight more in the returne,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:13132:35"/>then was abated in the forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
                  <p>And was <hi>Iacob</hi> glad to leaue his countrey, the land of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, to ſee his yonger ſonne <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> though in Egypt. What then ſhall bee the ſoules ioy to end a pilgrimage in a ſtrange land, and goe to ſee his elder brother Chriſt in heauen, an inheritance more pleaſant then that land of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen, freed from all the encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances of this Egypt? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid <hi>S. Paul, I deſire to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, that I may bee with Chriſt.</hi> For this tedious mortalitie, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant it how man can, will be intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, if death doe not disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then it; becauſe long liuing ſo loads vs with ſinne, as the burthen thereof tyres euery man at laſt. It is ſuch an inmate, as will rooſt in vs as long as life affords it houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roome: nor wil it lodge alone, but ſtill one ſinne will call in another: but through death, the very body of death, and burthen of ſinne, are
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13132:35"/>both caſt out together.</p>
                  <p>Sith then the life I now enioy, is beſet with death, tends to death, and ends in death, I will no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger miſtake tearmes, calling that death, which is life; and that life which is death. <hi>Hanc eſſe mortem, quam nos vitam putamus: Illam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, quam nos pro morte timemus,</hi> ſaid <hi>Lactantius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>More diuinely ſaid S. <hi>Auſtine, Per vitam ad mortem tranſitus eſt, per mortem ad vitam reditus eſt.</hi> Therefore the Pagans did not ill, to celebrate the day of their death with mirth; and the day of their birth with mourning. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſoule be then infuſed, when man is made;
<note place="margin">Death the regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule.</note> yet it is new borne, when man dyes. His bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die being the wombe, and death the midwife, which deliuers that to ſorrow, this to glory.</p>
                  <p>The Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſo little ioyed in his birth, that he ſaid, <hi>Let not the day wherein my mother bare me, be bleſſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:13132:36"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quis pauet? quis flet? quis eget? quis errat? Solus (heuſortes!) homo ſperat, optat alget, voluit, explorat, queritur. Malorum omnia plena,</hi> ſaid a diuine Poer.</p>
                  <p>But to aſſure there are ioyes in death. What ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vnto well dying men? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, and lift vp your heads, for now your Redemption draweth neere.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="division">
               <head>The third generall diuiſion. III.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>When Death is to be prepared for: and how.</head>
                  <p>IT was the ſaying of the diuine Philoſopher <hi>Plato.</hi> There is <hi>nulla ſalutar is Philoſophia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The time when.</note> but <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petua mortis meditatio:</hi> and <hi>ſine iſta meditatione tranquillo eſſe animo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo potest. Scipio</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>Mortis meditatio,</hi> Is <hi>vita ſapientis:</hi> and that it was the moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Philoſophy to ſtudy a mans
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13132:36"/>mortality. Politiques ſay, <hi>Totâvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ diſcendum eſt viuere.</hi> But ſaith <hi>Seneca; Hoc magis miraberis, Totâ vitâ diſcendum eſt mori.</hi> Fooles would faine doe in the end, that which wiſe men doe in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Prepare for their end: but careleſſe men thinke, that the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niory and gouernment of times is at their commands, to doe what they liſt, when they liſt. We haue little power ouer the preſent, much leſſe ouer the future. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>Dauid</hi> cryed betimes; <hi>Lord, let me know mine end, and the meaſure of my daies, what it is, and how long I haue to liue. All the daies of mine appointed time,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob, I wil watch, till my changing ſhall come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Change, the great Maſter of the world, that hath Time for his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, abuſes many men with the hope of time. It is true, Time is a ſeruant equall to all men: it holds pace, and flies as faſt in idleneſſe, as in buſineſſe; ſo as time wel ſpent, diminiſhes our time: yet when it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13132:37"/>is imployed in timely preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it layes vp time as treaſure for a future time, and ſo is rather a husbanding, then conſuming of time.</p>
                  <p>He liues in ſafety that watches his time. <hi>Diem perdidimus,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatian.</hi> But in reckoning of time, moſt men miſcaſt-time, counting that firſt which is laſt, and that laſt which is firſt; beginning our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt from the day of our Birth, whereas our deaths day is our firſt day. For in the accompt of life, our laſt day of life, is the firſt day to life. Wee then ceaſing to dye, when we leaue to liue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Solebat dicere Fabianus, In tria tempora vita diuiditur, quod eſt, quod fuit, quod futurum est, ex his, quod agimus breue est, quod acturiſumus, dubium, quod egimus, certum.</hi> Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon firſt with time paſt, and you may make time to come certaine: make your ſaluation certaine, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Scepticks put a <hi>fortaſſe</hi> vp
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13132:37"/>on all things in the world. But ſaid S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> there is no one thing in the world to be named, where this word <hi>fortaſſe</hi> had not place, except you ſpeake of death. <hi>Hîc ſolùm for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe locum habere non poteſt.</hi> Death, as it is ſaid of the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, comes not by obſeruation. He liues not, that knowes where, when, or how he ſhall dye: yet noneliues but knowes hee muſt dye. <hi>Mors omnibus finis, multis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me dium, quibuſdam votum, de nullis melius merita, quam quibus accidit antequam vocaretur.</hi> Therefore ſaid one, <hi>dementiae eſt,</hi> it is more then folly not to bee prepared for death. <hi>Sed ſi mors veniens praemedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur, tunc ſuperatur.</hi> The prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for death, is the fruition of life. <hi>Nemo propter Canos &amp; Rugas diu vixit:</hi> yet neuer man preſerued himſelfe from dying, by forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting death. The very Heathens, by natures inſtinct, prouided themſelues for death by ſacrifices to their gods.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:13132:38"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Frange toros, pete vina, roſas cape, fundere nardo;</l>
                     <l>— Ipſe iubet mortis te meminiſſe Deus.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaying,
<note place="margin">A faire way of dying well</note> 
                     <hi>the day of death was better then the day of birth,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred that there was a faire way of dying well: whereunto two things were moſt requiſite.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, a timely preparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore death. <hi>Nam facilè ſustinet, qui expectat mortem. Seneca</hi> ſaid, <hi>Saepe debemus mori, nec volumus; mors<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, nec volumus.</hi> Wee ought of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to prepare for death, and we will not: at laſt we dye indeed, and we would not. <hi>In hoc errore omnes verſamur, quòd non putamus, niſi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ad mortem vergere, citamur nec ſenſu, nec aetate. Mors quo faciliùs obrepat, ſub ipſovitae nomine latet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you intend preparation for death, you muſt auoid all procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination, <hi>Neſcis enim quid ſerus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper vehat.</hi> This <hi>vox Coruina,</hi> that alwayes cryes, <hi>Cras, cras,</hi> couzens many a man, making him <hi>perdere
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:13132:38"/>hodiernum,</hi> truſting vpon to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, ſaith <hi>Tibullus. I am mala finîſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem letho, ſed credula vitam ſpes alit, &amp; meliùs cras fore ſemper ait,</hi> but truſt not to that: <hi>Ille ſapit quiſquis, Poſthume, vixit Heri. Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ne gloriêris in crastinum, neſcis enim quid ſuperventur a pariet dies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By deferring, we preſume vpon that we haue not, and neglect that we haue. <hi>Quod in manu fortunae po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum eſt, diſponimus; quod in tua eſt, dimittis.</hi> Which made the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Poet, <hi>diuino furore inſtinctus,</hi> vtter <hi>hoc ſalutare carmen, Optima quaeque dies miſeris mortalibus aui, prima fugit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore, <hi>noli tardare,</hi> delay not thy prepare for death, til thou feeleſt the approaches of Death. <hi>Recordare nouiſſimum, &amp; non peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis in aeternum.</hi> Doe the worke of of the day <hi>in die ſuo.</hi> No man can promiſe himſelfe a morrow.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Fleres, ſi ſcires vnum tua te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pora menſem:</l>
                     <l>— Rides cùm non fit, forſitan, vna dies.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:13132:39"/>
                  <p>Euery man hath his day. <hi>Est &amp; dies hominis, &amp; dies Domini.</hi> When mans day is paſt, then Gods day comes.</p>
                  <p>The caſe therefore of thoſe men is moſtvnhappy, who after forty or fifty yeeres of dayes, in their miſ-ſpent time (for it was not <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> but <hi>tempus</hi>) and now ready to die, are euen then to learne how to dye, when they are in the Act of dying. <hi>Quae tam ſtulta mortalitatis obliuio, inde velle vitam incoare, quò pauci perduxerimus?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was a ſweet ſpeech, and might well haue become an elder body, which a yong innocent child vſed lying in extremity of ſickneſſe: Mother, what ſhall I doe, I ſhall dye, before I know what death is, I pray you tell mee what is death, and how I ſhould dye? Certainly, <hi>multum intereſt, peccare aliquis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit, an neſciat.</hi> But there is <hi>nil miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius morienti, quam neſcire mori;</hi> nay ſaith one, <hi>Tolerabilior eſt non eſſe, quam neſcire mori.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:13132:39"/>
                  <p>Since then it is a thing as well naturall, as neceſſarie for a man to dye, <hi>Quisquis ad ſummum peruenit, ad extremum properat.</hi> It is no thankes to a man to pay that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, which hee muſt doe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. But in paying of this debt, wiſedome counſels thee two things:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to conſider the time when.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the meanes or maner how.</p>
                  <p>For the time, ſeeke not death in the errour of thy life. <hi>Remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, while the euill dayes come not, nor the yeeres approach wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in you. Before the ſiluer cord bee looſed, or the golden ewer broken. Before the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond tree flouriſh, and the Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopper be a burthen. Before the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the houſe ſhall tremble, the ſtrong men bow, the grinders ceaſe. They waxe darke that looke out by the windowes, and the daughters of muſicke be brought low.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:13132:40"/>
                  <p>Old <hi>Barzillai,</hi> being in this caſe, refuſed all the pleaſures of a Kings houſe, though hee was gently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by King <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Age, or ſickneſſe, will make a man vnapt either to compoſe, or diſpoſe himſelfe to death. <hi>Tunc tibitarda ſluunt ingrata<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tempora.</hi> It is no good time then to prepare to die, when it is a burthen to liue.</p>
                  <p>Thy beſt health affoords but time good enough for this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therefore dedicate not all thy time to buſineſſe, for that as well as ſloth, may rob thee of thy time.</p>
                  <p>Doe you deſire ſome ſignes of death,
<note place="margin">Three ſignes of approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death.</note> before you take this courſe? <hi>Tres ſunt mortis nuntij, caſus, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitas, ſenectus. Caſus dubia infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas grauia, ſenectus certa denunciat. Caſus nuntiat mortem latentem, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitas apparentem, ſenectus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When man begins to be ſicke, his ſenſes are wholly buſied about the paines of the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:13132:40"/>
                  <q>I am vigor &amp; quaſſo languent in corpore vires.</q>
                  <p>The Phyſician is then confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with thee of the ſtate of thy body. The Lawyer is conſulted with, about thy worldly ſtate. The Miniſter touching thy ſoules health. Thy friends are then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome, ſtrangers trouble thee, viſites, offend thee: thy owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants cannot pleaſe thee, other mens diſcourſes tire thee, to ſpeake thy ſelfe ſpends thee, and to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent grieues thee, not to bee told how thou doeſt, vexes thee, to be told how ill thou art, diſcomforts thee; but it moſt of all afflicts thee, to ſee thy wife, children and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, weeping and lamenting by thee.</p>
                  <p>Thus miſerably we poore men at this time are diſtreſſed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, made vnfit for any thing, when, as God knowes, a due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to death, requires all the faculties and ſtrength, of a ſound, perfect, and whole man.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:13132:41"/>
                  <p>Euery man naturally, when hee comes neere the goale of death, euen for ſome intrinſicall cauſe, though vnknowne to himſelfe, is then weary of himſelfe, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines life with a tedious diſlike. <hi>Tunc iniucunda eſt rei poenitendae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordatio,</hi> diſtaſting euery thing, neglecting the very thought of all humane affaires.</p>
                  <q>Nec iuueni luſus qui placuere, iuuant.</q>
                  <p>But then thinkes, O how am I ſtraitned till it be accompliſhed!</p>
                  <p>This ſhould haue beene done when ſtrength of vnderſtanding ſerued. <hi>Nam ſerum eſt tunc viuere incipere, cum deſinendum est.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The little Bee, ſo ſoone as flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſpring, goes abroad, viewes the gay diapry, and the diuerſitie of the flowerie fields, ſuckes the choiſeſt of them, fraights her thighes, carries to her hiue, makes a cuurious combe, and ſo by times hoards vp honey in Summer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Winter. Why is the winter harder to the Graſhopper,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:13132:41"/>then to the Ant? onely prudencie and imprudency differs them.</p>
                  <p>Thinke not thou the winter of thine age, a time fit enough for this worke. <hi>Mauna</hi> muſt bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in the morning; it is too late to prepare when time is paſt before you begin.</p>
                  <p>Repentance alſo begun in the time of ſickneſſe,
<note place="margin">Repentance when to be practiſed.</note> is commonly as ſicke as the party, yeelding then, when it cannot reſiſt, and then preparing and repenting, when all other helps and hopes faile.</p>
                  <p>Sound repentance and fit prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration muſt both be timely, not then forſaking ſinne, when ſinne forſakes vs; and wiſhing time, when time is paſt. <hi>Omnis motus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalis velocior eſt in fine,</hi> the end of time, affoords little time.</p>
                  <p>Holy <hi>Iob</hi> tels vs, <hi>If thy bones be full of the ſinnes of thy youth, they will lie downe with thee in the duſt. Sed mortantur ante mortem vitia, &amp; ad iudicium non ſequantur.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death hath folded vp thy dayes, all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:13132:42"/>is paſt. The Cocke crowed, but that <hi>Gallicinium,</hi> ſo ſoft a voice could not awake thee. Therfore <hi>Signicinium,</hi> lowder mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, muſt end the Scene.</p>
                  <p>It is a great maſſe of ſinnes that we haue wound vp, in the dayes of a long miſ-led life; it will aske long time to vntwiſt this bottome; nay, to rauell it out in many ends, will aske great labour. Great labour, and little time, ſuite not: Therefore worke while it is day, <hi>The night commeth, when no man can worke.</hi> Vſe not time, as ill hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands doe their Farmes, let their Leaſe runne out, before they bee e're the better by their Farmes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Few and euill are the dayes</hi> of the longeſt liued man, and yet to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man there is a <hi>Triduum</hi> lent, the ſpace of three dayes at leaſt: but ſleepe not <hi>vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Quatriduum,</hi> leſt it be ſaid, <hi>Hee hath lyen foure dayes in the graue: Iam foetet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Flatter not thy ſelfe by the theeues example, who repented,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:13132:42"/>but in <hi>illa hora.</hi> That is not ſet for imitation, but to keepe from deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</p>
                  <p>It is a ſtrange thing to ſee, that old men wil not ſee death, though it be before their faces; nor young men, though it ſtand at their backes. The old gray-headed man to ſeeme young, had coloured his haire blacke; but the diuell told him hee would not bee ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zened.</p>
                  <q>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnes fall is, ſcit te Proſerpina canum.</q>
                  <p>The common faſhion is to put men in mind of their death, when we doubt they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not liue. Till the Phyſician findes ſome ill ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes, the patient may not bee diſ heartened with the name of death. But hee is the good Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian of my ſoule, that tells mee of death, when he ſees me liue in ſin.</p>
                  <p>There is not any man ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, who with his good wil would die in his ſinnes; yet moſt ſo liue, as if they beleeued permiſſion
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13132:43"/>were the Article of their faith all their life long: and the Article of remiſſion of ſinnes, were reſerued till the point of death.</p>
                  <p>But terrible will death be, when the dying man with griefe for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie loſt, will repent that euer he liued, and count it happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe enough, if then he might die and be no more. But that will not be, <hi>quia Mors eſt ſine morte. Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per viuit, ſemper occidit, ſed nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàmpraeoccidit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That which ends all, is without all end; Remember the parable of the fiue fooliſh virgins, and the faire warning Chriſt giues: <hi>Bee yee readie, for the Sonne of Man comes at an houre when yee looke not. Ecce venio ſicut fur;</hi> that is, when you ſleepe beſt, and thinke leaſt of him.</p>
                  <p>Now as it is wiſedome to bee prepared for death;
<note place="margin">Settlement in Religion, the beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiue for Death.</note> ſo if you will die with peace of conſcience, bee well reſolued in point of Religion before you die, neuer any man was
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13132:43"/>a looſer by beleeuing; for faith is euer recompenſed with glory; while thou liueſt it is not amiſſe to make doubts: but thou ſhalt finde it a fearefull thing, to die in doubt; and the happieſt thing vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to be well aſſured, and cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolued in the trueth of thy faith before thou dieſt. This done, then be of good cheere, for thou ſhalt heare Chriſt ſay vnto thy ſicke ſoule, as he ſaid vnto the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full woman, <hi>Goe in peace, thy faith hath ſaued thee.</hi> And let all concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted humaniſts remember what their maſter <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaid when he died: <hi>Anxius vixi, dubius morior. O Ens entium, miſerere mei.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now of the way to die well.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non eſt res magna viuere: Hoc omnes faciunt: ſed pauci bene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuntur. Et illi Mors grauis iucum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, qui notus omnibus, ignotus moritur ſibi.</hi> Man is readie to die before hee liues, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore liued in the world, that hee might die to the world, <hi>his yeeres
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13132:44"/>come to an end, as a tale that is told:</hi> his dayes deceiue him, for they paſſe as a ſhadow by Moone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine, then appearing longeſt, when they draw neereſt to an end. Wee that now liue, liue by death; for had not Chriſt dyed, wee had not liued. Therefore ſaith S. <hi>Paul, My life is not deare vnto mee, ſo as I may finiſh my courſe with ioy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doe you deſire to liue a long time: the ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> ſaith, <hi>A man that is made perfect in a ſhort time, fulfils a long time. Et vita ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, ſi ſcias vti, longa eſt. Vir bonus bis viuit,</hi> ſaith the Spaniard. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>liat at at is ſpatium ſibi vir bonus, hoc eſt viuere bis, vita poſſe priore frui</hi> He liues twice, that leades his firſt life well. <hi>Alexander</hi> had a good account of his age, reckoning by victories, not by dayes. So ſhould Chriſtians count their dayes by euery ſinne they conquer in that day. Numbring of dayes, ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> is not <hi>numerus die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13132:44"/>quis ſit,</hi> but, <hi>quî ſit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tres ſunt dies hominis,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Hierom, Dies Conditionis, dies Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſionis, dies Reſurrectionis. One day certifieth another,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid.</hi> Time lent vs, flyes away in the time that is lent, euery moment comming, being the death of that is paſt: But weigh well euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for it is of ſo great moment, as that vpon it depends eternity of time to come.</p>
                  <p>Vnto dying well, there are three things moſt requiſite.
<note place="margin">Three things requiſite to dying well.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, to bee often meditating vpon death.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to be dying dayly.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to dye by little and little.</p>
                  <p>Often meditation of Death,
<note place="margin">The firſt ſtep to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well.</note> brings you to die in eaſe, alleuiates paines, expels feares, eaſes cares, cures ſinnes, corrects death it ſelfe. <hi>Quo modo non morimur, cùm viuitur mortuis?</hi> wee liue with ſo many deaths about vs, that wee cannot but often thinke of dying.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:13132:45"/>Euery humour in vs engenders a diſeaſe enough to kill vs, ſo that our bodies are but liuing graues, and we die, not becauſe wee are ſicke, but becauſe wee liue, and when we recouer ſickneſſe, wee eſcape not death, but the diſeaſe.</p>
                  <p>Doe then as the Preacher coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; what you haue to doe, that doe quickely; For in the graue, whither thou goeſt, there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worke, nor diſcourſe, nor tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, nor wiſedome, nor conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, nor fruition of any thing; all is entombed in ſilence, darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ouerſhadowing it.</p>
                  <p>Meaſure not life, <hi>ſpatio, ſed actu,</hi> becauſe life is ordained for Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not for fruition. If thou haſt any good to doe for the Church, the Commonwealth, or thy Friends, doe it quickly. Haſt thou much goods laid vp in ſtore? make thee friends with thy Mammon, but ſing not a <hi>requiem</hi> to thy ſoule; ſay not vainely, <hi>Viuamus dum viuimus, ſors fortuna vt volet,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13132:45"/>ordinet: vita iam in tuto eſt.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Hac nocte:</hi> know, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the day of vanitie, comes the night of Iudgement: then both light and delight goe out toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Sadly and ſuddenly ſhalt thou find all worldly pleaſures turned into waking dreames: <hi>Et quae pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſti, cuius erunt?</hi> All the towers in the ayre that thou haſt built, <hi>Vno ictu proſternentur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>On the other ſide, doeſt thou eate the bread of carefulneſſe, and drinke the water of weariſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction? Heere is <hi>Manna,</hi> bread from heauen, and water after which <hi>non ſities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is no ſuch cordiall to comfort cares, or temper ſorrows, as often and ſeriouſly to thinke of death, and to be acquainted with it betimes;
<note place="margin">Priuacie with death, a ſouereigne cordiall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt death.</note> for through acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, death will leeſe his horror: like vnto an ill face, though it be as formidable as a Monſter; yet often viewing will make it fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, and free it from diſtaſte.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:13132:46"/>
                  <p>It is ſaid that <hi>Philoſtrates</hi> liued ſeuen yeeres in his tombe, that hee might be acquainted with it againſt his bones came to lye in it. Some Philoſophers haue beene ſo rapt in this Contemplation of Death and Immortalitie, that they diſcourſe ſo familiarly and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingly of it, as if a faire death were to bee preferred, before a pleaſant life.</p>
                  <p>This is well for Natures part,
<note place="margin">Where the power of death lyeth.</note> and Moraliſts thinke it enough for their part, but Chriſtians muſt goe further, and ſearch deeper. They muſt ſearch where the power of death lies: They ſhall finde that the power of euery particular mans death, lyes in his owne ſins, that death neuer hurts a man, but with his owne weapon: it alwayes turnes vpon vs ſome ſin it findes in vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſting of death is ſinne.</hi> Plucke out the ſting, death cannot hurt. <hi>Quid huius viuere est, diû mori?</hi> Dye often, and you ſhall be ſure to dye well.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:13132:46"/>
                  <p>The ſecond ſtep to dying well,
<note place="margin">The ſecond ſtep.</note> is to dye dayly. <hi>Morior, ne moriar,</hi> I dye dayly, ſaith S. <hi>Paul. Singulos dies, ſingulas vitas putae; qui enim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dies tanquàm vitam ordinat, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinum nec optat, nec timet.</hi> The old ſaying is as good, Doe that euery day, which thou wouldeſt doe the ſame day that thou dyeſt. <hi>Bonum est conſumere vitam ante mortem:</hi> Make that voluntarie, which is neceſſarie, and yeeld that quickly as a gift, which you muſt pay as a debt at laſt. Did men know that death were onely an end of life, and no more: euery man for his owne ends would bee a diſturber of the worlds peace while hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and ſeeke to make his owne but when he dyed. Hee that dies daily, ſeldome dies deiectedly: ſo he that will liue when he dies, muſt dye while hee liues. <hi>The widow that liues in pleaſure</hi> (ſaid Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>is dead while ſhee liues.</hi> Liue holily &amp; you ſhal die happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Studeto talem eſſe in vita qualem
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:13132:47"/>velis reperiri in morte.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A liuing man is ſubiect to a double death:
<note place="margin">Two ſorts of death, where to euery man liuing is ſubiect.</note> The one natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, the other ſpirituall. Naturall death doth but ſeparate the bodie from the ſoule: But the ſpirituall death ſeparates the ſoule from God. Of all other, it is the moſt deſperate ſtate of life to liue natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and to bee dead ſpiritually: <hi>Thou haſt a name to liue, but thou art dead,</hi> ſaid Saint <hi>Iohn.</hi> but of the Prodigall child returned from his euill wayes, it is ſaid, <hi>This my ſonne was dead, but is now aliue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee count it a fearefull thing for a man to bee author of his owne death. A ſinfull life ſlayes the ſoule, and ſo while we liue, we kill or loſe our better life. The commandement that ſayes, <hi>Thou ſhalt dee no murder,</hi> ſpecially for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the murthering of our owne ſoules: but certainly that which depriues vs of our better life, makes of all other the worſt death.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:13132:47"/>
                  <p>It is therefore a holy wiſedome for a man to let his ſins go before him. <hi>Moriantur ante te vitia.</hi> They to die <hi>actually,</hi> thou heere <hi>virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally:</hi> and ſo to liue, that when thou art to die, thou haue nothing to doe but die. Atchieuement of riches, pleaſures, honours, haue beene painefull; yet if theſe things leaue not vs by accident, we leaue them by death, and at our death we ſhall plainely tell them, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid, <hi>Miſerable comforters are you all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If life delight, then vſe it, yet ſo, as a Traueller doth his Inne, for a night and away, and in thy iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney follow not the common tracke. <hi>Nam ad Deum faciens iter, per trita ſi itur, longiùs abitur.</hi> But do as the doubtful paſſenger, aske queſtions of euery one you meete, that can ſet you in your right way. Herein bee as great a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſt as were thoſe religious La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Rome, who neuer let Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> reſt for queſtions,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:13132:48"/>which was the readieſt way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. If a man would but compare the Forenoone of his age with the Afternoone, how long the one is and how ſhort the other is, euery man would be dying dayly. <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marios poſuiſti dies.</hi> The longeſt liuer hath but a handfull of dayes. Life it ſelfe is but a circle, alwayes beginning where it ends.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Erat, quando non erat; ſed erit.</hi> Time was, when man was not. But how late a beginning ſoeuer man had, yet after death hee ſhall be ſure neuer to ſee end. With the <hi>Ancient of dayes</hi> there are no dayes: And the time ſhall be, when time ſhall be no more.</p>
                  <p>There be two common errours which deceiue moſt men:
<note place="margin">Two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon errors.</note> Firſt, that a man enters not into eternall life, till he dyes: when as his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling heere begins his life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. To <hi>Zacheus</hi> (Chriſt ſaid) <hi>This day is ſaluation come vnto thy houſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Faith preuents time, and makes
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:13132:48"/>things future, preſent. The godly man that hath his preſent life hid with Chriſt in God, ſo liues heere, as if his conuerſation were in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, carrying himſelfe not onely honeſtly, ciuilly and humanely; but beyond naturall condition, his life ſeemes ſuper-humane, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and ſpirituall.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond errour is that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer a man liues, yet if at laſt he ſeeme to die well, then, all is well, and his ſoule is ſure to bee ſaued: this is a bold and a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conceit; for though Miſery be the obiect of Mercy, and Hope the miſerable mans god; yet hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane life hath not a greater friend, nor many times a greater foe, then Hope.</p>
                  <p>Many would dye, did not hope ſuſtaine them: more haue dyed, flattered with vaine hope. Whoſo hopes too much, cozens himſelfe at laſt. <hi>Be not deceiued, God is not mocked: not euery one that ſaith, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:13132:49"/>Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> In this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life enter into the firſt degree of life eternall or thou mayeſt die eternally, with <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon vs</hi> in thy mouth. But haue thy part heere in the firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which is from ſinne to Grace: and then thou ſhalt enioy the ſecond Reſurrection, which is from duſt to Glory.</p>
                  <p>The third ſtep to well dying,
<note place="margin">To die by little and little, the third ſtep.</note> is to die by little and little <hi>Totâ die mortificamur.</hi> Naturally wee are euery day dying by degrees. The faculties of our mind, the ſtrength of our bodies, our common ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes euery day decaying <hi>paulatim.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that vſeth this courſe, euery day to dye by little and little, to him let death come when it will, it cannot be either terrible or ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine. If wee keepe a Courſer to runne a Race, wee leade him euery day ouer the place to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him by degrees with all things by the way; that when he comes vpon his ſpeed, he doe not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:13132:49"/>ſtart or turne aſide for any thing he ſees: So let vs enure our ſoules and then wee ſhall run with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <hi>the race that is ſet before vs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To die by little and little, is firſt to mortifie our leſſer ſinnes, and not to ſay with <hi>Lot, Is it not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle one?</hi> Wee may not waſh our hands from crying and from bloody ſinnes, and yet hugge in our boſome ſome beloued and Herodian ſinne. Certainely great ſinnes will neuer be conquered, if little ſinnes be cheriſhed. Saint <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> writing conſolatory Epiſtles, to the Martyres of his time, told them that he that once hath ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come death in his owne perſon, doth dayly ouercome him in his members: if you mortifie the members of your fleſh by little and little, you will not feare the crueltie of any exquiſite death the Tyrant can deuiſe.</p>
                  <p>There be a ſort of little deathes, as ſickneſſe of body, troubles of minde, loſſe of friends, and the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:13132:50"/>like: vſe theſe rightly in their kinde, and you may make them kindely helpes to dying well.</p>
                  <p>The right way to bring any thing to a good end, is to proceed by degrees. God himſelfe made nothing abſolute at firſt. This great God loues to haue degrees kept degreeingly: to grow to greatneſſe is the courſe of the world, ſo by little and little to goe out of the world, <hi>per gradus,</hi> not <hi>per ſaltum,</hi> is the way to Heauen. Let a man goe out of the world, as he came into the world, which was, firſt by a life of <hi>Vegetation,</hi> then of <hi>Senſe,</hi> afterwards of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Dauid</hi> preſcribes vs this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when hee ſayes, <hi>Doce me &amp; duce me, Domine.</hi> Hee will not runnetill hee bee taught to goe. <hi>Teach mee to doe thy will, and leade me into the land:</hi> What land is that? There is <hi>terra quam terimus:</hi> land on earth, which yeelds vs all pleaſures, that's not it. There is <hi>terra quam gerimus,</hi> refined earth,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:13132:50"/>beautified bodies which we beare about vs, nor is this it. There is, <hi>terra quam quaerimus:</hi> the glorious land of promiſe, that's the land we ſeeke. Into this land, <hi>duce me, Domine.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For the manner of dying.</head>
                  <p>AMongſt men it is a matter of chiefe marke, the manner of a mans death. All men, as men, die naturally; as Chriſtians, they ſhould die religiouſly. The good man equally can die, or liue, for he knowes if hee liue: God will protect him, if he dyes, God will receiue him. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in a Contemplation of Death, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geminates the word, ſaying. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Domine; exitus Mortis. The iſſues of Death belong to thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A good man by his good will would die praying and doe as the pilgrim doth, goe on his way ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſo addes the paine of ſinging, to that of going. Yet by this Surplus of paine, vnwearies
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:13132:51"/>himſelfe of paine. But ſome wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thinke God rather curious, then they faulty, if a few ſighes, with a Lord haue mercy vpon vs, be not enough at the laſt gaſpe.</p>
                  <p>There is no ſpectacle in the world ſo profitable, or more terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then to behold a dying man: to ſtand by, and ſee a man diſman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Curiouſly diddeſt thou make man <hi>in the loweſt part of the earth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid:</hi>) but to ſee thoſe elements which compounded made the body, to ſee theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, and the man to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued is rufull. So dependant is the life of man, that it cannot want one element. Fire and Ayre, theſe fly vpward. Water and Earth, they ſinke downeward. So liuing man, becomes a dead carkaſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seneca</hi> thought a man might chooſe his own death, which was ſome eaſe to him. <hi>Quemadmodum nauim elegam nauigaturus, &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum habitaturus: Ita mortem vti<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> quá ſum exiturus è vita.</hi> But bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:13132:51"/>ſaith another, <hi>Stultè haec cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur: vitam alijs approbare quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam debet, mortem verò ſibi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſince it is ſo great a matter to die, ſo neceſſarie to die well, ſo dangerous to die ill: Let your life be an acting of death.</p>
                  <p>Certainely Death hath great dependancie on the courſe of a mans life. There bee many that chooſe rather to die quickely, then to liue long ſickely. Some that will inuite Death to doe them the kindneſſe to take them ſoone out of the world, counting a ſhort death, the happieſt houre of a mans life. And for this (ſaith <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>) a man is moſt beholding to Nature. <hi>Quòd vnum introitum ad vitam dedit, exitus vero multos. Sed non ſic itur ad aſtra.</hi> Chriſtians know better wayes, as how to liue in grace, that they may die in peace. And to whom this grace is giuen, for him glory is reſerued, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> Many a good man is ſore troubled to ſee men of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:13132:52"/>the beſt liues, to haue diſtempered and perplexed ends. Some rauing, ſome deſpairing, ſome dying ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and ſeldome haue any ſo bitter draughts, as thoſe whom God loues beſt.</p>
                  <p>It is fit therefore to take notice of the cauſes that be naturall. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire in dying, may ariſe as well from weakenes of nature, as from trouble of minde: but in neither caſe can this preiudice him that hath liued well. <hi>Marke the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and behold the perfect man, for the end of that man is peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rauings, and other ſtrange paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, are many times rather the effect of the diſeaſe, then mouing from the minde. For vpon deaths approaches, choler fuming to the braine, wil cauſe diſtempers in the moſt patient ſoule. In theſe caſes the faireſt and trueſt iudgement that can be made, is, that ſinnes of ſickneſſe, occaſioned by violence of the diſeaſe in a patient man, are but ſinnes of infirmitie, and not to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:13132:52"/>be taken as ill ſignes or preſages: I will not deſpaire in reſpect of that mans impatient dying, whom the worme of conſcience had not troubled, or deuoured liuing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> in this caſe, the better to make his way, prayed, and cryed, <hi>Lord, ſpare mee a little, O ſpare me, that I may recouer ſtrength, before I goe hence and be no more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Indeede to <hi>Ezekias</hi> ſome yeeres of dayes were lent, but we are not worthy of that fauour, wee muſt time it as we may, and bee content to liue and die at vncertainties.</p>
                  <p>As a ſicke man hearkens to the clocke, ſo let vs watch Death. For ſudden comming of death, finding a weake ſoule vnprepared, makes it deſperate, leaues it miſerable.</p>
                  <p>Sudden death of it ſelfe is not therefore euill,
<note place="margin">What death is to bee counted ſuddaine.</note> becauſe it is ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: but becauſe it may take vs away ſuddenly, our ſoules vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared. The good man neuer dyes vnprepared, becauſe his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance in goodneſſe, is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:13132:53"/>againſt ſudden death.</p>
                  <p>If a man bee alwayes prepared, and haue ſet all euen betwixt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and his conſcience; ſudden death is but a quicker paſſage to heauen, and is not to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a ſudden death, but a ſudden departure, becauſe it came not vnlookt for.</p>
                  <p>Though the righteous be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by Death (ſaith the Booke of Wiſedome) yet ſhall hee bee at reſt, becauſe hee hath made his peace beforehand. His departure is no miſerie, for his hope is full of eternitie. <hi>Ezekiel</hi> the Prophet (ſo often ſtiled <hi>Sonne of man</hi>) to him God ſayes, <hi>I take away from thee the delight of thine eyes,</hi> (which was his wife) <hi>with a ſtroke ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>yet thou ſhalt not weepe.</hi> Let not the preſent pleaſures of this life allure thee, nor the cares thereof poſſeſſe thee, and ſudden death cannot ſurpriſe thee. <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſa nulls Mors, cui prouida Vita.</hi> But if a man doe not prepare to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:13132:53"/>die, he may liue ſeuen yeeres in a conſumption, and yet die a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den death. For any time is ſudden to him that is vnprepared.</p>
                  <p>They take their marke amiſſe, who iudge a man by his outward behauiour in his death. If you know the goodneſſe of a mans life, iudge him not by the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his death. When a man comes to bee iudged, his life, and not the manner of his death, ſhall giue the euidence with him, or againſt him. Many that liue wickedly, would ſeeme to die ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily, more for feare to be damned, then for any loue to goodneſſe. To theſe men there is <hi>malum tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex, quod manet in ſeptima.</hi> Which is <hi>Horrour in exitu. Dolor in tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitu. Pudor in conſpectu Dei.</hi> If my life pleaſe God, I am ſure my death ſhall pleaſe me: for hee that liues well, is ſure to die well: but he that liues ill, is not ſure to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e well. <hi>Vitae praeſentis finem, talem eſſe oportet, quale futurae eſt principium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:13132:54"/>
                  <p>It is a great happineſſe to die in eaſe. <hi>Quis tam facile, quando vult, dormit,</hi> as he that layes downe his life in peace. Yet a good man doth not alwayes die in the exerciſe of his goodneſſe. But as a wiſe man when hee ſleepes, leeſes not his knowledge; no more doth a good man his graces, though he die in diſtemper. For habitudes of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doe not then leaue him, though they cannot then do their office for him.</p>
                  <p>But the vulgar opinion, if a man die quietly, and goe away like a lambe (which in Conſumptions and dul diſeaſes, all men doe) then ſure hee goes to Heauen. But if he die diſtempered, and of franticke behauiour (which happens to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny through extreame inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) then ſure he goes to hell, is a iudgement from nature, not of Religion; and in this caſe truſt not Natures iudgement, for it is arted with ſubtilties of phyſicke.</p>
                  <p>Serenitie, ioy and peace in a
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:13132:54"/>dying man, is a hopefull behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: yet wee ſee the cleere ſtarres that are ſo delightfull to behold, bring forth their Rayes by ſparke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and dartings, as though they were deliuered of their light by trauell and hard aſſayes. So good men in their death, haue great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of accidents, many languors, many agonies, many iterated en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours, trauailing of Death, as in a Childbirth. But when the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of the ſoule lye open to God without oppoſition of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cares; then it peaceably makes egreſſe with a ſweetneſſe, and without diſturbance.</p>
                  <p>Naturall cauſes haue their ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; but it is the God of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that commands them. It is Gods propertie ſometimes to worke ſupernaturally by nature.</p>
                  <p>But truſt to this, beleeue aright and liue as you beleeue, and you ſhall be ſure to die in ſafety: and the way to end life quietly, is to render it willingly.</p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:13132:55"/>
                  <p>Let no contentment of the world ſo fixe you to the world; as to make you deſire longer life. <hi>Saepe in hoc eſſe, Bene, non diu.</hi> Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life is no vnhappineſſe. <hi>Citiùs mori vel tardiùs, adrem non pertinet; bene mori aut malè, adrem ſpectat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Booke of Wiſedome ſaith, <hi>Hee was ſuddenly taken away, leaſt ill ſhould alter his vnderſtanding, or deceit beguile his ſoule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Had preſent death beene euill, or long life good, <hi>Cain</hi> had beene ſlaine, and <hi>Abel</hi> had ſuruiued. But Death commonly begins firſt, where God loues beſt. <hi>His ſoule,</hi> ſaith the ſonne of <hi>Sirach, pleaſed God; therefore haſted hee to take him away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee ſee the beſt men liue not longeſt. And indeede it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious to wiſh that goodneſſe ſhould hinder any man from hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. Hee that lends good men to the world, owes them a better turne then to let them
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:13132:55"/>liue long in the world.</p>
                  <p>One man ſeemes to die caſually, another violently, both by deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, all men by Decree.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dederat curſum natura, peregi,</hi> ſaid the Poet. But the Diuine tels vs, though <hi>Moſes</hi> dyed vpon one Hill, <hi>Aaron</hi> vpon another Hill: yet both where they might ſee the land of Promiſe.</p>
                  <p>How familiarly did <hi>Moſes</hi> heare of Death, when there was no more betwixt God and him, But, <hi>Moſes goe vp and dye?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With ſuch a ſociable compella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are good men inuited to Death, as to a Feaſt.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nec mihi Mors grauis eſt</l>
                     <l>poſituro morte labores.</l>
                     <l>— Mors mihi merces erit.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The aſſurance of life after Death.</head>
                  <p>ALthough my fleſh bee eaten with wormes,
<note place="margin">Aſſurance of life after death.</note> theſe wormes turned to duſt, this duſt blowne through the earth, yet after thou
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:13132:56"/>haſt <hi>turned all to deſtruction: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine thou ſayeſt, Come againe you children of men. Redemptor meus,</hi> is the word of aſſurance, <hi>My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and your Father,</hi> ſaith the Goſpel. <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> are words of Aſſurance to mens ſoules, though in mens ſtates they make all Controuerſies. <hi>I know that my Redeemer liueth.</hi> How doe I know it? not by Opinion, but by Faith. <hi>Fides non creditur, ſed cernitur.</hi> Things are not ſo, becauſe we are perſwaded they are ſo: but becauſe they bee ſo, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee are ſo perſwaded. The woman with child, knowes ſhee is with child, when ſhee feeles it ſtirre liuely: So the Spirit of God aſſures our ſpirit, when wee feele his Spirit in vs.</p>
                  <p>Holy <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>Though after the skinne wormes deſtroy the body yet in my fleſh I ſhall ſee God for my ſelfe, and mine owne eyes ſhall behold him, and not an others.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which numerall Identity giues
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:13132:56"/>certaintie, that this ſoule of mine, imperſonated anew, and ſo inani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating my body againe, ſhall giue a new being, and a better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto both.</p>
                  <p>That ſoule, the loſt pearle, which to finde a man would haue giuen all that he had, ſhal there be found ingrauen in gold, where as heere it was found ſet but in clay.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="division">
               <head>The fourth generall diuiſion. IIII.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>What our last thoughts ſhould be.</head>
                  <p>AS in greateſt extremities, good Phyſicians leaue drugges, and miniſter onely Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials: ſo deale by thy ſoule when death approaches, caſt away all worldly cares, entertaine onely thoughts that will animate thy weake body, and refreſh thy thirſtie ſoule, as did that <hi>dew of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:13132:57"/>Hermon,</hi> falling vpon the <hi>Hill of Sion:</hi> nor will I feare how this body of mine ſhall appeare an other day. For I am promiſed by him that will performe, it ſhall not be found naked: But this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering of fleſh being caſt off, I ſhall take this body againe cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with <hi>glory,</hi> as with an other <hi>garment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This doth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> moſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly and diuinely expreſſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Wee know, that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, wee haue a building giuen of God, that is, a houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the heaueus. For therefore wee ſigh, and deſire to be cloathed with our houſe, which is from heauen: Becauſe, that if wee be cloathed, wee ſhall not be found na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. For</hi> indeede, <hi>we that are in this Tabernacle, figh and are burthened, becauſe we would not be vncloathed, but cloathed vpon, that immortalitie might be ſwallowed vp of life. And hee that hath created vs for this
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:13132:57"/>thing, is God, who alſo hath giuen vs the earneſt of his Spirit. Therefore we are alwayes bold, though we know that whilſt we are at home in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, wee are abſent from the Lord. For wee walke by faith, and not by ſight. Neuertheleſſe, we are bold and loue rather to remoue out of the body, and to dwell with the Lord.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>This is ſo promiſing and ſo ſweet, as it ſeemes, to tranſport a man aliue from earth to Heauen. <hi>Hîc in via es, ſed illic eris in Patria.</hi> Therefore baite not too long vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pleaſures by the way. All the while I liued, ſaid a good man, I was going on my iourney to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my countrey: but now that I am dying, I finde my ſelfe neere home, I am now come to Mount Sion the Citie of the liuing God, the heauenly Hieruſalem.</p>
                  <p>I will not therefore ſit downe on this ſide Iordane, but haſten to the Citie; whither when I come, I ſhall there ſee my God face to face: Heare my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:13132:58"/>ſay, <hi>Euge, bone ſerue. It is my Fathers will to giue thee a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Is it not enough, that my God is gone vp to prepare a place for me, but will hee giue mee a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome alſo? And ſhall not I bee glad, when God ſhall come and fetch mee to inthrone mee in this kingdome? <hi>Abſit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now mee thinkes I heare my ſoule ſay, <hi>Cur non accedis, Domine? Quid moraris?</hi> I haue too long dwelt in this ſepulchre of earth. <hi>And woe is me, that I ſtill remaine in Meſech, and dwell in theſe tents of Kedar. It is enough, Lord,</hi> as <hi>Elias</hi> ſaid in the wilderneſſe, <hi>Take now away my life, for I am no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then my Fathers were.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, my ſoule is now growne ſo high minded, that ſhee ſaith, <hi>Maior ſum, &amp; ad maiora genitus, quàm vt mancipium ſim huius cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris.</hi> Thus rich in thoughts, and great in expectation, doth diuine Contemplation make vs.</p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:13132:58"/>
                  <p>God hath not giuen a ſoule to any creature elſe but Man: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is but duety in Man to know the dignitie of his Soule, which is ſo heauenly ambitious, as it will not let heauen alone, till it may ſee, as it is ſeene.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Grauata eſt anima mea,</hi> my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is a burthen to my ſoule. It hath had honour enough to haue beene ſo long companion with my Soule: wherefore now as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaid, <hi>Egredere, anima, egredere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Hermite ſitting on his turft, ſaid to his ſoule, <hi>Sexaginta annos ſeruiuiſti Deo, &amp; nunc mori times?</hi> Goe out of this Arke of fleſh, O my ſoule, for I ſmell the ſauour of reſt. <hi>Celeritas nunc in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderio, mora eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Though my ſoule, as a bird, for neceſſitie ſake, hath been faine to ſtay awhile heere vpon earth; yet willingly would ſhe be ſoring in the skies. But I finde that <hi>ista vita eſt mihi impedimento ad id,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:13132:59"/>propter quod viuitur.</hi> Specially when I heare my Sauiour ſay, <hi>Father, I will that thoſe whom thou haſt giuen mee, be with mee alſo where I am: That they may behold my glory. To him that is faithfull vntill death, I will giue a Crowne of life.</hi> Therefore, <hi>deſiderio deſideraui ergaſtuli huius egreſſum,</hi> that I may ſee <hi>facie ad faciem,</hi> him whom my ſoule loueth, and to bee (Lord) where thou enioyeſt thy ſelfe, and glorified ſpirits en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy thee.</p>
                  <p>Entertaine thy laſt houres with ſuch like thoughts. <hi>Et hatibi da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt ad aeternitatem Iter, &amp; in iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ſubleuabunt.</hi> They will An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelize thy body, and imparadiſe thy ſoule, before thou commeſt into Heauen; yeeld a ſweetneſſe, farre beyond the bitterneſſe of Death.</p>
                  <p>Certainely, a good ſoule, thus imploying it ſelfe, in <hi>iſta hora,</hi> will not leaue the felicitie it ſhall haue in ſuch a tranſmigration from
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:13132:59"/>death to life, for all the ioyes that life paſt did euer render her.</p>
                  <p>Good Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> in a high ſpeculation, endeuouring to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this heauenly ioy, was as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by a graue old man: Father <hi>Auſtine, quid agis?</hi> A man may as well draw in all the ayre in the world with one breath, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe to the life that which thou art now about. Though this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable ioy cannot bee expreſſed: yet it is <hi>res generoſa conari alta, &amp; mente maiora concipere, quàm quae effici poſſunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore this wee may doe, ſome way ſample that which wee can no way expreſſe.</p>
                  <p>Looke as a Bird that hath been long encaged, then chants it moſt merrily, when ſhe gets looſe into the open ayre.</p>
                  <q>— Nititur in ſyluas qua<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> redireſuas:</q>
                  <p>Or as a ſicke man, that hath wearily toſſed and turned himſelfe in his bed all night, is them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:13132:60"/>when hee ſees the day breake, and the ſunne beames guild the morning:</p>
                  <p>Or as a priſoner that feeles his chaines heauy vpon him, longs for releaſement.</p>
                  <q>— Libera<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> â ferris crura futura velit:</q>
                  <p>So it will bee with thy Soule, when thou ſhalt heare thy Sauiour ſay, <hi>I am thy ſaluation. Come vnto mee thou that art weary and heauy laden, and I will refreſh thee. Poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentibus &amp; petentibus pertinet Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Coelorum</hi> To them that are weary of this durance, and ſue for deliuerance, belongeth the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore as a wearied trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler that hath paſſed a long iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney (though perhaps met with ſome delights by the way) is then gladdeſt, when hee comes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in kenning of his countrey.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Natale ſolum dulcedine cunctos du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</hi> Euen ſo thy ſoule, after many yeeres pilgrimage in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:13132:60"/>of the world, being come with <hi>Moſes</hi> to Mount Nebo, and beholding the pleaſant land of Canaan from the top of Piſgah, will then laugh for ioy, as doth the Horizon, to ſee the Sunne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>as a Bridegroome out of his chamber. Dilectus meus deſcendit ad hortum ſuum, ad areolam aromatum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of this ioy, thy dazled eyes might haue ſome glimpſes, when thou waſt in health: but then it was as the blind mans viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Goſpel, to whoſe firſt ſight men ſeemed to <hi>walke like trees.</hi> But in this thy new ſtate, thou ſhalt ſee clearely men and Angels ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lambes Throne, and heare thy ſelfe inuited to the Lambes Supper, where <hi>thou ſhalt be brought into the wine ſeller, and loue will be the banner ouer thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come then,</hi> O Shunammite, <hi>ſtay me with flagons, and comfort me with Apples, for I am ſicke of loue: Kiſſe me with the kiſſes of thy mouth, for
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:13132:61"/>thy loue is better then wine; Shew mee, O thou whom my ſoule loueth, where thou feedeſt, where thou lyeſt at noone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus with <hi>Solomon</hi> in a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, and with <hi>Dauid</hi> in a Pſalme, let be the Raptures of thy Soule, which, as in trance, ſhall bee caught vp to Heauen, as was <hi>Philip</hi> by the Spirit, or <hi>Abdias</hi> by the Angel.</p>
                  <p>And with an Heroicall alacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, tempered with a gracious humilitie, giue vp thy ſoule to God, and bid farewell to the world.</p>
                  <p>It was S. <hi>Bernards, I ſhall neuer truely ioy till I heare this word. Come you bleſſed; Nor ceaſe to ſorrow till this be paſt; Goe ye curſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dying Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> before his eyes were cloſed, had a faciall fight of his Sauiour, <hi>looked ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly into heauen, and ſaw the glory of God, and Ieſus ſtanding at the right hand of God.</hi> And old <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> after hee had ſeene his Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:13132:61"/>then reioyced to ſay, <hi>Lord now lettest thou thy ſeruant depart in peace, for mine eyes haue ſeene thy Saluation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Hoc videa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; moriar. Morior, vt videam.</q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE RAPTVRE OF THE SOVLE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RApitur anima, cùm coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtia Contemplatur, &amp; contemplando iucundatur.</hi> And becauſe ſight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes delight; Therefore Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would faine aſcend to viſion. But that's a priuiledge for Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> It ſo diuinely rauiſhes, as it raiſes in man towring thoughts, irradiates his ſoule with high ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions; yea, ſo it eleuates mans ſoule to God, as it takes him out of himſelfe, to liue aboue himſelfe. The Soule being thus powerfully attracted by the faire inducements of ſo diuine delight,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:13132:62"/>She on her party correſponds, and with a willing aſſent glides after theſe attracts: And as a vapour exhaled by the Sun, ſhee goes out of her ſelfe, would willingly draw the body with her, but that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is too ſad: wherefore ſhee quitts it, as not agil, and ſpritefull enough to ſoare ſo high.</p>
               <p>It is an admirable thing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that the eye of a man, ſo weake a creature, ſhould looke vp euery day to heauen, ſo wonderfull in height, and yet neuer bee tyred by the way. But by this I ſee, that heauenly Contemplation, if it be ſtrong enough, and not ouer-clog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with earthy thoughts, is able to carry vs with caſe to heauenly extaſie: but then there muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the will and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, from things <hi>ſublunarie,</hi> to things <hi>heauenly.</hi> For the will takes pleaſure to perceiue the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding taken into Rapture; and when as the faculties both of will and vnderſtanding, doe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:13132:62"/>their rauiſhments, then are we ſweetly brought into diuine extaſie.</p>
               <p>Of this ſacred extaſie, the Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Diuines make diuersſorts: One of Vnderſtanding a ſecond of Affection, a third of Action.</p>
               <p>Action is well added, for a man is not to bee aboue himſelfe in Contemplation, and vnder him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in Conuerſation.</p>
               <p>The firſt of the three is in <hi>Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore.</hi> The ſecond in <hi>Feruore.</hi> The third in <hi>Labore.</hi> The one cauſed by Admiration, the other by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, the laſt by Operation.</p>
               <p>In theſe Raptures, the Fathers who were ſtiled Saints had ſuch a complacency, as they ſtroue to act this as the way of a new life, ſometime before their Death, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as the Votaries would ſay: Neuer was Saint but had Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie and rauiſhment of life before his death. They laboured by a liquefaction of their ſoules into God, to Inſoule themſelues in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:13132:63"/>God: to put their foules out of the naturall comportment of the body, and ſo to liue in diuine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, without liuing in the body.</p>
               <p>Some ſo liued, as it was doubted whether they were liuing-men dead, or dead-men liuing: nay ſome, with feruency of ſpirit, were tranſported into ſuch Extaſie, that their ſoules being wholly conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in diuine Contemplation, they cared not to afford common aſſiſtance to Nature, and ſo haue dyed through exinanition and want of ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Thus did loue performe the office of Death. <hi>Loue is as ſtrong as Death,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon;</hi> nay with them it wrought more then death could doe. For death onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth by effect, that which loue operated by affection.</p>
               <p>Death did but ſeparate their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies from their ſoules. But loue ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated their ſoules from their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. In ſuch a trance they report Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> to ſay, <hi>O God thou
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:13132:63"/>onely art all mine, when ſhall I bee wholly thine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Bernard</hi> to ſay, <hi>What is there in heauen, or what deſire I on earth, but thee, O Lord? Thou art the God of my heart, and my eternall portion, my Soule is ſatisfied with nothing, but to be with thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> to ſay, <hi>The ſoule of</hi> Ionathan <hi>was knit to</hi> Dauid; <hi>but my ſoule is glued vnto thee, O Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S. Hierome</hi> to ſay; <hi>O my Sauicur, diddeſt thou die of loue for mee? A loue more delorous then death: but to me, a death more louely, then loue it ſelfe. I cannot liue, loue thee, and be longer from thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Baſil</hi> to ſay, <hi>That</hi> Iacob, <hi>when hee had faſt hold on God, let him goe for a bleſſing:</hi> but the Shunamite, <hi>My ſoule will not let thee goe ſo.</hi> For ſhe now ſeekes no more Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, but to enioy the God of Benedictions.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Sauernius</hi> the Indian Saint, was recouering from dying, it is reported hee was heard to ſay,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:13132:64"/>
                  <hi>O my God, doe not for pitie ſo ouerioy me, if I muſt liue ſtill, and haue ſuch conſolations, take me to heauen. For he that hath once taſted this and thy ſweetneſſe, muſt neceſſarily liue in bitterneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the ſtate of loues life in God, which giueth a ſuper-hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Being vnto man, man being yet on earth. So that this ardent loue, neuer ſatiated heere, hauing ingrafted mee into God by her vniting vertue, makes me now ſay <hi>Viuo ego, ſed non ego: viuit verò in me Chriſtus. My life is hid in Chriſt with God.</hi> And though my Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our be hidden from my corporall eyes in God, as God was hidden in him, while hee liued heere on earth; yet now me thinkes I ſee him face to face. <hi>Viſione beatificâ, &amp; iugitèr reuelatâ facie, Sponſi gloriam ſpeculando, transformatur anima de claritate in claritatem: Audet &amp; ipſa loqui,</hi> 
                  <q>Tota pulchraes amica mea.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:13132:64"/>
            <head>MORTIS EPILOGVS.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>QVoniam mors me quotidiè expectat, ego mortem quotidiè expectabo.</hi> But before thou goeſt, conſider well theſe foure things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndevenis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Quò vadis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Quides.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>Quid eris.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Vpon enquiry <hi>vndè venio,</hi> I am told,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peccatores peccatorem me in peccato genuerunt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Miſeri miſerum me in hanc lucis miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam induxerunt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Conceptus culpa. Naſci miſeria. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuere paena. Mors Anguſtia. Et quantò eſt vita mea longior, tantò eſt culpa mea numeroſier.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This makes me to thinke, <q>Quorſum commodata eſt mihi vita humana?</q>
            </p>
            <p>For this onely,
<q>
                  <l>Ad comparandum vitam coeleſtem:</l>
                  <l>Et hoc vult diuina clementia,</l>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:13132:65"/>
                  <l>Quòd vita mea ſit breuior,</l>
                  <l>Vt labor meus ſit leuior.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>For my, <hi>Quò vado.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IT is lifes <hi>Poſy, Vadere,</hi> to fade and decay.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vado</hi> tels me I am in <hi>tranſitu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But it reioyces mee to thinke,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eo ad Patres.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And this promiſe comforts,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sepelieris in aetate bonâ.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therefore <hi>nec me taedet viuere, nec</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>timeo mori:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mihienim Mors ſeruit in ſolatium vitae.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itam habeo in Patientia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mortem verò in deſiderio.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plangam ergo Paulatim dolorem meum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et tunc</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oblitus exilij Ibo ad Patriam: nam</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mortuâ morte reuertitur mihi Chriſtus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>To expreſſe, <hi>Quid ſum.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>QVis fando explicare queat?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Puluis &amp; Aer,</hi> this I know;</l>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:13132:65"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Et in puluerom reuertêris.</hi> This is ſure.</l>
                  <l>That <hi>homo</hi> is <hi>Morbidum, putre, caſſum;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This euery man findes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Homo de humore liquido;</hi> This is our metall,</l>
                  <l>And the mould is no better, <hi>In vtere impuro,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Damnatus antequàm natus,</hi> that's our Condition.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Semen Abrahae;</hi> thats our beſt Stocke.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dicens putredini; Thou art my Mother,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to the Wormes, <hi>You are my Brethren.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <list>
                  <head>So heere is our great kindred.</head>
                  <item>Our dwelling is, <hi>Inter pulices &amp; culi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> amongſt Flyes and Fleas.</item>
                  <item>Our qualitie is vile and baſe, lighter then vanity, there is our waight.</item>
                  <item>A thing of nothing, that's our worth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Et in non hominem vertitur omnis homo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>There is our end.</item>
               </list>
               <p>What then is our being?
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Somnium &amp; dolor eſt tota vita hominis,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:13132:66"/>cùm creſcit vita, decreſcit. Vita ipſa non eſt vita, ſed vmbra mortis &amp; figura vitae.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Flentes naſcimur; In labore viuimus; In dolore morimur.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Then certainly
<q>
                     <l>Si natus ſum plorans,</l>
                     <l>Si morior plangens,</l>
                     <l>Nolo egoviuere ridens.</l>
                     <l>Hoc tantum volo.</l>
                     <l>Animam meam ornare quae Deo &amp; Angelis</l>
                     <l>mox praeſentenda eſt in coelis.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now for, <hi>Quid eris.</hi> This alſo I know.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>QVodſum, &amp; me noneſſe, ſcio. Sedid eſſe &amp; nôſſe deſidero.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Num videre Deum, viuere cum Deo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eſſe in Deo, &amp; habere Deum:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haec eſt aeterna ſecuritas &amp; ſecura aeternitas.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This may be admired, but cannot be througly vnderſtood:</l>
                  <l>Yet better vnderſtood, then can be expreſſed.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:13132:66"/>
               <p>Therefore to my ſoule I ſay not,
<q>
                     <l>O Animula, blandula vagula: <hi>but,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>O Anima Dei inſignita imagine,</l>
                     <l>Decorata ſimilitudine,</l>
                     <l>Deſponſata Fide,</l>
                     <l>Redempta Sanguine,</l>
                     <l>Dotata Spiritu,</l>
                     <l>Deputata cum Angelis,</l>
                     <l>Quidtibi cum Carne?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But to contemplate <q>Quanta claritas, quanta ſuauitas, quanta iucunditas maneat te in illa viſione, cùm facie ad faciem videbis Chriſtum?</q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Erratae.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. line 2 is <hi>redundat.</hi> pag. 18. line 23. <hi>fawnes</hi> pro fannes. p. 19. l. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Diſeere,</hi> pro Deſere. p 29. l. 12. <hi>the threats,</hi> pro for threats. p. 30. l. 6. <hi>animas,</hi> but <hi>ſuas,</hi> pro animas ſuas, but p. 30. li. 7. <hi>Inde,</hi> pro Iudae p. 36. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. <hi>conu ncun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> pro comminuunt. p 38. l. 23. <hi>we chinke,</hi> pro wee would thinke. p. 51. l. 23. <hi>amaze,</hi> pro amuſe p. 41. l. 8 <hi>amicum,</hi> pro annulum p. 74 l. vltima. <hi>Tolerabili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> pro Tolerabilius. p. 80 l. 4 <hi>Signicinium,</hi> pro Cygnicinium. p. 92. l. 7. <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marios,</hi> pro Palmares.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
